<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The sinners acquittance. A checke to curiositie. The safest seruice Deliuered in three sermons at the court. By Iohn Denison Doctor of Diuinity, and one of his Maiesties chaplaines then in attendance.</title>
            <author>Denison, John, d. 1629.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 157 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 82 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B12377</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6594</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114588</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849813</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849813</idno>
            <idno type="VID">177921</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B12377)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177921)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1269:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The sinners acquittance. A checke to curiositie. The safest seruice Deliuered in three sermons at the court. By Iohn Denison Doctor of Diuinity, and one of his Maiesties chaplaines then in attendance.</title>
                  <author>Denison, John, d. 1629.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 136 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Legatt, and are to be sold by Iohn Budge, at the signe of the Greene Dragon in Paules Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A checke to curiosity; and The safest seruice" has separate title page dated 1624; pagination and register are continuous.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:177921:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>THE SINNERS ACQVITTANCE. <hi>A Checke to Curioſitie. The ſafeſt Seruice.</hi> Deliuered in three Sermons at the Court. <hi>BY</hi> IOHN DENISON Doctor of Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and one of his Maieſties Chaplaines then in Attendance.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by IOHN LEGATT, and are to be ſold by <hi>Iohn Budge,</hi> at the ſigne of the <hi>Greene Dragon</hi> in <hi>Paules</hi> Church-yard. 1624.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <group>
               <text xml:lang="eng">
                  <front>
                     <div type="title_page">
                        <pb facs="tcp:177921:2"/>
                        <pb facs="tcp:177921:2"/>
                        <p>THE SINNERS ACQVITTANCE. A Sermon preached before the KING at <hi>Greenewich, May</hi> 4. 1623. <hi>BY</hi> IOHN DENISON Doctor of Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and one of his Maieſties Chaplaines.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by IOHN LEGATT, and are to be ſold by <hi>Iohn Budge,</hi> at the ſigne of the Greene Dragon in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1624.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="dedication">
                        <pb facs="tcp:177921:3"/>
                        <pb facs="tcp:177921:3"/>
                        <head>TO THE RIGHT Honourable and Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Father in GOD, IOHN Lord Biſhop of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> Lord <hi>Keeper</hi> of the Great Seale of <hi>England,</hi> and one of His Maieſties moſt Honourable Priuy Counſell.</head>
                        <p>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable and Reuerend, I preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, long ſince, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of a better preſent,
<note place="margin">Lord <hi>Elſmere</hi> Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celor of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
                           </note> to Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate my Act Sermon to that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Lord (my honourable Maſter) who now reſts in peace, and found acceptance. Whom, me thinkes, J
<pb facs="tcp:177921:4"/>ſee in part deſcribed, when I reade that of <hi>Poſſeuin,</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the excellent Hiſtorian <hi>Thucydides</hi> who is ſtiled by him,
<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Poſſeuin. de Hiſtoricis, Sect.</hi> 2.</note> 
                           <hi>Acutus, concitatus; ner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoſus, denſus, ſolidus, &amp; ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens.</hi> And I may adde that which was eminent in that noble Lord (an eſpeciall note of ſolide iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) his Conſtancie. For (as <hi>Tully</hi> ſpeakes of <hi>Cato) grauita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem perpetua conſtantia ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borauit.</hi>
                           <note place="margin">
                              <hi>Cicero de Offic. lib.</hi> 1.</note> He was not like <hi>Alci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biades, in conciliandis ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citijs, quam in retinendis vir melior;</hi> But did ratherimitate that famous Emperour <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus Caeſar;</hi>
                           <note place="margin">
                              <hi>Sueton. in Auguſt. Caeſar. Cap.</hi> 66.</note> 
                           <hi>Qui amicitias ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que facilè admiſit, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiſſime
<pb facs="tcp:177921:4"/>retinuit.</hi> But that which did crowne all his naturall and morall parts, was his pious care and courſes in furniſhing the Lords vineyard with good labourers. For he conferred not preferments for gaine, but freely, and nobly. And (that which was extraordinarily honourable) hee rather enquired after well deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing men, then ſtayed till be was ſued to. I write what ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue done, and many, I doubt not wil ingenuouſly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. Now, your Lordſhip ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing beene to that noble Lord <hi>(ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit inuidia verbo)</hi> like the belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Diſciple to our Sauiour,
<note place="margin">Saint <hi>Iohn.</hi>
                           </note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſing with him in matters di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine
<pb facs="tcp:177921:5"/>and humane, and ſucceeding him both in the ſeat and actions of Honour, with generall applauſe: I haue beene emboldened to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent vnto your Lordſhip theſe Sermons, which many my worthy friends in Court haue much deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and to whom, for the publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them, I am by promiſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged.</p>
                        <p>The God of heauen multiplie his bleſsings vpon you, to the good of this Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>Your Lordſhips humbly deuoted,</hi> Iohn Deniſon.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </front>
                  <body>
                     <div type="sermon">
                        <pb n="1" facs="tcp:177921:5"/>
                        <head>THE SINNERS ACQVITTANCE. A Sermon preached be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King at GREENE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>WICH, <hi>May.</hi> 4. 1623.</head>
                        <epigraph>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>ISAI. 53.4.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>Surely he hath borne our infirmities, and carried our ſorrowes.</p>
                           </q>
                        </epigraph>
                        <p>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E reade in the firſt of <hi>Samuel,</hi> and the ninth,
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 9.9.</note> that the Prophets, in ancient time, were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Seers,</hi> becauſe that from that watch-tower of diuine ſpeculation they ſaw that which
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:177921:6"/>others ſaw not;
<note place="margin">Hierom. ad Paulin.</note> or, as Saint <hi>Hierom</hi> ſaith, <hi>Eum quem caeteri non videbant, Him whom others ſaw not.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Amongſt the Prophets ſome were more eminent and excellent then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and amongſt them all, none comparable to the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> who was amongſt the Prophets,
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 9.2.</note> like <hi>Saul</hi> amongſt the Iſraelites, higher then the reſt by the ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders vpward.</p>
                        <p>It is ſaid of <hi>Abraham,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Iohn 8.56.</note> that he ſaw our Sauiours dayes, and ſo did <hi>Iſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi> who, albeit he liued aboue ſixe hundred yeares before Chriſt was borne, doth ſet forth his birth, life, and death ſo liuely, as though hee had ſeen all things acted, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed before his eyes.
<note place="margin">Hieron. quo ſupra.</note> Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, that S. <hi>Hierom</hi> ſaith, <hi>Non tam Propheta dicendus ſit, quam Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſta, He may rather be called an Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt, then a Prophet,</hi> and may ſeeme rather to haue written a Hiſtory, then a Propheſie, whereof, this
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:177921:6"/>which I haue read may be called an Abſtract, &amp; it is indeed an Epitome of the Goſpell.</p>
                        <p>It may be fitly diuided into a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, and a propheticall Hiſtory.
<note place="margin">Generall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Preface is briefe, in this one word, <hi>Surely.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Hiſtory is not long, it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines but fiue words in the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew, and not many you ſee in the Engliſh; <hi>Hee hath borne our infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and carried our ſorrowes.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Preface is briefe, but mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall, it giues aſſurance of the truth of the Hiſtory, which one fitly compares to the eyes of a man: For,
<note place="margin">Polybius.</note> as the eyes of a man put out, leaue the body a meere truncke: ſo, the truth remooued from an Hiſtory, leaues it a vaine diſcourſe.</p>
                        <p>The Hiſtory is not long, but full; it containes matter admirable, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable, comfortable. Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, in reſpect of him who is the glory of the Hiſtory, euen <hi>the Lord
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:177921:7"/>of glory.</hi> Lamentable, in regard of what he ſuſtained, that is, infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſorrowes. Comfortable, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of them for whom hee bare them; they were our infirmities, our ſorrowes.</p>
                        <p>I may ſay of this Scripture in S. <hi>Chryſoſtomes</hi> words;
<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Chryſ. in Gen. hom.</hi> 8.</note> 
                           <hi>Etſi verba ſint pauca, magnus tamen theſaurus in il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis eſt reconditus;</hi> Though the words be few, yet they containe a great deale of rich treaſure. This ſentence is like <hi>Iacobs</hi> Ladder, wee cannot ſpare one round of it. It is a gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſentence, and the leaſt parcell thereof is more worth then all the gold of <hi>Ophir.</hi> Wee will therefore diligently ſearch the minde.</p>
                        <div type="preface">
                           <head>The Preface.</head>
                           <p>ANd firſt to beginne with the Preface. The word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap> 
                              <hi>Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> may be either <hi>Vox distinguentis,</hi>
                              <pb n="5" facs="tcp:177921:7"/>or <hi>aſſeuerantis,</hi> either a word of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction, or aſſeueration. A word of diſtinction, and ſo the vulgar Tranſlater may ſeeme to haue taken it; for he renders it, <hi>verè tulit, Hee hath truely borne our infirmities.</hi> The Prieſts, in the time of the Law were ſaid <hi>to beare the ſinnes of the people, Leuit.</hi> 10.17. But they bare them typically, he truely; hee bare them, not in figure, but in fact, not in type, but in truth. Againe, hee bare them not <hi>imaginariè,</hi> imaginarily, and in outward appearance onely,
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Tertul. aduerſ. Marc.</hi> 4.8. <hi>Auguſt. de hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ. ad quod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vul. har.</hi> 46.</note> as the abſurd <hi>Manichees</hi> and <hi>Marcion</hi> held; but as he was a man, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>, in nature and truth (as <hi>Damaſcen</hi> ſaith) ſo did he beare our infirmities, and carry our ſorrowes <hi>verè, ſicut verus homo,</hi> truely, as being truely a man,
<note place="margin">Aquin. in loc.</note> as <hi>Aquinas</hi> interprets the word. It was not with our Sauiour, as with the three Children in the third of <hi>Daniel,</hi> who came forth of the fiery furnace,
<note place="margin">Dan. 3.17.</note> 
                              <hi>not hauing their
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:177921:8"/>haire ſindged,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Plutarch. in vita Coriol.</note> 
                              <hi>nor their garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged:</hi> But rather, as <hi>Coriolanus multas oſtenderet cicatrices,</hi> could ſhew ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Cicatrices of the wounds recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the warres. So our bleſſed Sauiour could giue the like demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratiue ſatisfaction, to the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credulous <hi>Thomas.</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Ioh. 21.27.</note> Let them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, who talke of an imaginarie Paſſion, expect an imaginarie Salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; We know that our Sauiour bare our infirmities truly.</p>
                           <p>Againe, the word may be <hi>vox aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuerantis,</hi> a vehement aſſeueration. And that, both to ſtop the mouth of a ſtubborne Iew, and to ſtrengthen the Faith of an humble Chriſtian. So is the word vſed,
<note place="margin">Gen. 28.16.</note> 
                              <hi>Gen.</hi> 28. where <hi>Iacob</hi> beholding in a viſion the Lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, whoſe foot ſtood vpon Earth, and the top reached to Heauen, the Angels aſcending, and deſcending, ſaid comfortably, and confidently, <hi>Surely God is in this place.</hi> And ſo, the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> beholding by
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:177921:8"/>the eye of Prophecie Chriſt Ieſus in his deiected eſtate; ſaid no leſſe comfortably and confidently, <hi>Surely he hath borne our infirmities, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried our ſorrowes.</hi> Yea he ſo ſpeakes of it, as though Chriſt had done it, when the Prophet ſpake it; which was ſo indeed by way of myſterie: For <hi>Christ is the Lambe of God,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Reu. 13.8.</note> 
                              <hi>ſlaine from the beginning of the world.</hi> But it is rather ſpoken in a propheticall manner, in regard of future cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie.</p>
                           <p>As the Lord was <hi>Oculus propheta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> the eye of the Prophets; ſo were the Prophets <hi>Os Domini,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Luk. 1.70.</note> the mouth of the Lord: So that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they ſaw, or ſaid, in their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticall Office, muſt needes be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed. We muſt therefore take heed of <hi>Eues</hi> incredulitie,
<note place="margin">Gen. 2.17.</note> which cleaues cloſe to her poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. When the Lord had ſaid to <hi>Adam,</hi> by way of aſſeueration (as the Hebrew phraſe imports <hi>Morien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:177921:9"/>morieris,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Gen. 3.3.</note> thou ſhalt ſurely dye, <hi>Eue</hi> comes in with her addubitation <hi>Ne forte moriamur,</hi> leſt we dye. The Lord will not ſuffer any word of his Prophets to fall to the ground, and the truth of this Propheſie experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence hath manifeſted, and the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Euangeliſts, the Lords holy Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorians, haue recorded for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the Church to the end of the world.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="part">
                           <head>The Hiſtorie.</head>
                           <p>SO much for the Preface; Now to the Hiſtorie; wherein may it pleaſe you to obſerue</p>
                           <p n="1">1 The Perſon eſpecially mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the ſame, in the word <hi>He,</hi> that is, Chriſt.</p>
                           <p n="2">2 His Action; <hi>He hath borne, he hath carried.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="3">3 The burdens he hath borne and carried, they were <hi>infirmities, ſorrowes.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <pb n="9" facs="tcp:177921:9"/>
                           <p n="4">4 For whom he bare them: they were <hi>our</hi> infirmities, <hi>our</hi> ſorrowes.</p>
                           <p>I may ſay of this Text, as the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of Samaria ſpake of <hi>Iacobs</hi> well, The well is deepe,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 4.11.</note> and it hath diuers ſprings, which muſt be ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that we may from thence draw the water of Conſolation.</p>
                           <p>The pronowne <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>, <hi>He,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">The Perſon eſpecially mentioned.</note> is often ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenced and included in the verbe, but is here expreſſed, as being verie emphaticall. He, either by way of <hi>Admiration,</hi> or <hi>Exception.</hi> By way of Admiration; And it is admirable indeed, if either you conſider the dignitie of his Perſon, or the indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of his Paſſion. He that was the Sonne of God,
<note place="margin">Coloſ. 2.13. 1. Cor. 2.8.</note> yea <hi>the Sonne of his Loue, Coloſ.</hi> 1. He that was <hi>the Lord of Glorie,</hi> 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 2. He to whom the glorious Angels doe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, <hi>Hebrew.</hi> 1.
<note place="margin">Hebr. 1.6.</note> 
                              <hi>Hee bare our infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, and caried our ſorrowes.</hi> Well might it haue agreed to his excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Nature to haue conferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:177921:10"/>but to ſuffer torments, it was ſtrange, admirable. His Perſon, and Paſſion, in diſcourſe of humane rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, are verie incompetible.</p>
                           <p>Againe, <hi>He</hi> by way of exception, that is, He and none but He. <hi>He,</hi> who <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap> 
                              <hi>by himſelfe,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Heb. 1.3.</note> 
                              <hi>hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged our ſinnes.</hi>
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Aug. de temp. Hom.</hi> 108.</note> 
                              <hi>He, Qui ſordes om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium ſolus poſſet abluere,</hi> who him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe alone was able to waſh away all our ſinnes, ſaith S. <hi>Auſtin. He</hi> alone entred the liſts, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke the combate againſt Satan, as <hi>Dauid</hi> did againſt <hi>Goliah,</hi> when all the Iſraelites were meere ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and to him belongs the glory of the victory.
<note place="margin">Sueton. in vita Aug. Caeſar.</note> When <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> deſired <hi>two</hi> Conſuls to bee ioyned with him in Office, the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate denied it, as holding it a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent diminution of his dignitie, that one ſhould be ioyned in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulſhip with him, that was ſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy. And ſurely it muſt needs dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate from our Sauiours dignitie,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:177921:10"/>that any one ſhould be his copart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in the worke of our redemption. <hi>He trode the wine preſſe alone;</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Iſa. 63.3.</note> and <hi>there is no other name giuen vnder heauen, by which we muſt be ſaued.</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Act 4.12.</note> And ſo I come from the perſon to his actions.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="part">
                           <head>His Actions.</head>
                           <p>THe word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>, he hath borne, is a word of a large extent: Yet hath it two ſpeciall ſignifications, which fitly agree with theſe acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our Sauiour.</p>
                           <p n="1">1. It ſignifies in <hi>humeros tollere,</hi> to take vp a burden vpon ones ſhoulders; and ſo is it vſed in the 12. of <hi>Ezechiel;</hi> Now what this burden is, the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſhewes, when he complaines, in the 38. <hi>Pſalme,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Pſal. 38 4.</note> 
                              <hi>My ſinnes are gone ouer my head, and are as a heauy burden, too heauy for me to beare.</hi> And ſo the ſeptuagint tranſlate it, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>, <hi>He carried our ſinnes.</hi> This
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:177921:11"/>burden of our ſinnes did our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our beare vpon the croſſe,
<note place="margin">Thom. Aquin.</note> 
                              <hi>Vt vas noſter</hi> by way of imputation <hi>as our ſuretie,</hi> and the burden of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, due to our ſinnes, <hi>forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter</hi> in his perſon actually. Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that in the firſt Epiſtle of <hi>Peter,</hi> the ſecond chapter, <hi>Who, his owne ſelfe,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.24.</note> 
                              <hi>bare our ſinnes, in his owne body, on the tree.</hi> Therefore <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> hath obſerued,
<note place="margin">Chryſ. in loc.</note> that the Prophet ſaith not, <hi>Curauit,</hi> but <hi>por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tauit,</hi> Not, he cured, but caried, Yea tooke them to himſelfe: As if a Phiſition, forth of his cure, and for the cure of his patient, ſhould take the diſeaſe vpon himſelfe. So, <hi>tulit in ſe, vt a nobis tolleret,</hi> he tooke them vpon himſelfe, that he might take them from vs.</p>
                           <p>Againe, the word ſignifies <hi>auferre to take away;</hi> And ſo it is vſed in the 32.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 32.5.</note> 
                              <hi>Pſalme.</hi> For whereas our tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlations haue it, <hi>Thou forgaueſt the puniſhment of my ſinne,</hi> it is in the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:177921:11"/>Hebrew <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap> 
                              <hi>thou tookeſt away the puniſhment of my ſinne.</hi> And ſo the word agrees very fitly to our bleſſed Sauiour: for his <hi>pertulit,</hi> was an <hi>abſtulit,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Tertull adv. Marc.</hi> 4.10.</note> as <hi>Tertullian</hi> inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prets it, in his fourth booke againſt <hi>Marcion.</hi> Chriſt, when hee bare our ſinnes, tooke them away, Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that in the ſecond to the Coloſſians,
<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 2.14.</note> 
                              <hi>He tooke away the hand writing that was againſt vs, and nai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it on his croſſe.</hi> The bond of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, which <hi>Adam</hi> had forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Ambroſ. de Sacrament. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 4.</note> Chriſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged by his actiue and paſſiue obedience, and ſo cancelled it on the Croſſe. Therefore <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> pointing at our Sauiour, might very well ſay, <hi>Be hold the Lambe of God,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Ioh. 1.19.</note> 
                              <hi>that taketh away the ſinnes of the world.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>The word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>, <hi>he hath carried,</hi> Albeit in the Engliſh it differs not from the other, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap> 
                              <hi>hee hath borne,</hi> yet doth it in the Hebrew:
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:177921:12"/>For the one ſignifies <hi>Onus ipſum tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lere;</hi> the other, <hi>Onus impoſitum goe ſtare;</hi> as a learned linguiſt diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſheth them;
<note place="margin">Pagim.</note> that is, <hi>to take vp a burden, &amp; to beare a burden impoſed,</hi> and ſo both words may be well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to our Sauiour Chriſt. For, <hi>tulit,</hi> he tooke vpon him the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den voluntarily;
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Hieron. in Eſai.</hi> 53.</note> 
                              <hi>Crucem ſuſtinuit voluntate, non neceſſitate,</hi> His death on the Croſſe was voluntary, not of neceſſitie: according to his words in the tenth of <hi>Iohn,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Ioh 10.18.</note> 
                              <hi>No man taketh my life from me, but I lay it downe for my ſheepe.</hi> And <hi>portauit,</hi> he carried the burden impoſed, as it is in the ſixt verſe of this chapter: <hi>The Lord hath laid vpon him the iniquitie of vs all.</hi> Thus, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.32.</note> 
                              <hi>God gaue Chriſt for vs, Rom.</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Gal. 2.20.</note> 8. And, <hi>Chriſt</hi> alſo <hi>gaue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for vs, Gal.</hi> 2. So may it be ſaid, that God laid the burthen vpon Chriſt, and that Chriſt alſo tooke vp the burden. For here mercy and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:177921:12"/>truth met together:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 85.10.</note> God exacting our debt as a ſtrict creditor, and Chriſt diſcharging it as a cheerefull Redeemer. And ſo ſaith S. <hi>Bernard,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Bern. panoſ. Hebd. ſer.</hi> 4.</note> 
                              <hi>Chriſtus inuita paſſivam habuit acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem, in morte paſſionem activam ſuſtinuit.</hi> As Chriſt had a paſſiue action in his life; ſo had he an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue paſſion in his death, it was vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="part">
                           <head>His Burdens.</head>
                           <p>NOw to the burdens he beare, and carried, they were infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities and ſorrowes.</p>
                           <p>The Hebrew word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>, infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, ſignifies any corporall paine or anguiſh, proceeding from ſome part that is ſmitten or hurt. As in the tenth verſe it is ſaid,
<note place="margin">Mich. 6.13.</note> 
                              <hi>The Lord would breake, or bruiſe him, to make him ſubiect to infirmities:</hi> and in the ſixt of <hi>Michea, I will make thee ſicke with ſmiting.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <pb n="16" facs="tcp:177921:13"/>
                           <p>Thus our Sauiours body was ſubiect <hi>Laeſioni, &amp; ſenſui laeſionis,</hi> both to outward violence, and to the ſenſe of it. Though not <hi>reſpectu primae cauſae,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Aquin. par.</hi> 3. <hi>quae.</hi> 15: <hi>art.</hi> 5.</note> yet <hi>propinquae,</hi> as the Schooleman ſaith; Not in reſpect of ſin inherent, but in reſpect of the principles of nature. For he volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily tooke ſuch a body as was ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to hurt, and conſequently to paine.</p>
                           <p>The word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap> imports ſome ſenſible ſorrow, or anguiſh of the ſoule. <hi>As his body was ſubiect to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall afflictions,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Tulit corporis ſenſus, &amp; ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi affectus. Leo de paſſione ſerm.</hi> 7. <hi>Hier. in Loc.</hi>
                              </note> 
                              <hi>ſo was his ſoule to ſorrowfull affections.</hi> And ſo S. <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> diſtinguiſheth theſe words, <hi>Corpus habuit flagellatum, animum verè doluiſſe,</hi> &amp;c. As his body was ſcourged, ſo his ſoule was grieued; and this griefe was exceeding great. Euen <hi>a ſword of ſorrow did pierce through his ſoule,</hi> as <hi>Simeon</hi> ſpake of the bleſſed virgin in the ſecond of Saint <hi>Luke.</hi> Therfore he is called,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:177921:13"/>
                              <hi>Vir dolorum,</hi> A man of ſorrowes:
<note place="margin">Verſe 3. of this chapter.</note> which Hebrew phraſe, imports ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame ſorrow, like that, <hi>vir ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> a bloody man:
<note place="margin">2. Sam. 16.8.</note> and ſurely his ſorrow was exceeding great, as his mournefull ſpeech doth manifeſt, <hi>My ſoule is very ſorrowfull,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Mark. 14.34.</note> 
                              <hi>euen to the death.</hi> Therefore the ancient fathers haue applyed to him Ieruſalems mournefull complaint, in the firſt of the Lamentations of <hi>Ieremy.</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Lam. 1.12.</note> 
                              <hi>Was there euer ſorrow like my ſorrow?</hi> Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalems ſorrow might be ſuch, in her apprehenſion, as could not be matched; but our Sauiours was ſuch, in the truth of compariſon, as could not be paralleld. The Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts doe expreſſe this anguiſh of our Sauiours ſoule, by diuers preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing words;
<note place="margin">Math. 26.38.</note> as <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap> to be ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap> to be grieuouſly trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled: <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap> to be ſore amazed.
<note place="margin">
                                 <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                                    <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                                 </gap>.</note> His ſorrow was an immediate ſtroke vpon the ſoule, according to the etymon of the word. It is ſaid
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:177921:14"/>in the tenth verſe, that God ſtrooke him, and ſo did the Iewes, they ſtrooke his body in malice towards him, God ſtrooke his ſoule in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy towards vs. <hi>Iob</hi> complaines in his ſixt chapter.
<note place="margin">Iob 6.4.</note> 
                              <hi>The terrors of the Lord doe ſet themſelues in aray a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me.</hi> And ſo doth our Sauiour in the fourteenth of <hi>Marke,</hi> 
                              <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>,
<note place="margin">Mar. 14.34.</note> 
                              <hi>My ſoule is inuironed with ſorrow on euery ſide.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Such was the ſorrow of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, it was an immediate paſſion of the ſoule. As his ſoule did ſuffer, by way of ſympathy, when his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy was tormented; ſo did his body, when his ſoule was wounded. For when he ſweat droppes of blood, no hand of externall violence came neere him, it was the anguiſh of ſoule, that caſt him into that bloody ſweat. And this was neceſſary: For as S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſaith, <hi>Totus homo pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rijt, &amp; totus ſaluatore indiguit;</hi> As <hi>Adam</hi> ſinned both in body and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:177921:14"/>ſoule, ſo he needed a Sauiour both of body and ſoule: which that Chriſt might be, it was neceſſary that he ſhould ſuffer both in bodie and ſoule. And as the ſoule of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> ſinned by immediate action, ſo the ſoule of Chriſt ſuffered by an immediate paſſion. Yea as the ſoule was the firſt agent in the tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; ſo is it here the firſt patient in the affliction. For the firſt act of this Tragedie was in the garden of <hi>Gethſemane,</hi> and there did that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh ſeaze vpon his ſoule, before the ſpeare or nailes, or thornes did touch him.</p>
                           <p>And whence proceeded this ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and anguiſh, but from the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate hand of God that ſtrooke him? Otherwiſe it were ſtrange, that our Sauiour ſhould be brought into this extreamitie. Is it credible, as S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Auguſt. in Pſal.</hi> 93.</note> 
                              <hi>Vt Paulus ſervus exultet, Christus Imperator tristis ſit,</hi> that <hi>Paul</hi> the ſeruant ſhould
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:177921:15"/>triumph, &amp; Chriſt the Lord ſhould bee troubled in ſuſtaining of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, were it not, that both the hand of God and man was vpon him? Now, how farre this ſtroke of God, and ſorrow of our Sauiour proceeded, it is beyond the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of men, yea, the contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of Angels. It grieues my ſoule to ſee how ſome doe extenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, others doe aggrauate it. It ſhall be our modeſty not to attempt the gaging of it, our happineſſe, that we neuer feele it.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="part">
                           <head>For whom Chriſt bare theſe burdens.</head>
                           <p>VVE are in the next place to conſider, for whom our Sauiour bare theſe infirmities, and ſorrowes, and the affix <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap> 
                              <hi>ours</hi> doth appropriate them; they were our infirmities, our ſorrowes; they were ours by way of appropriati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, though his by way of imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:177921:15"/>
                              <hi>Peccat Aemylius, Rutilius plecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> Wee ſinned, and hee was puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed; <hi>We as ſheepe went aſtray,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Eſay 53.6, 7.</note> 
                              <hi>hee as a ſheepe was brought to the ſlaughter. Doles, domine, non tua, ſed mea vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nera,</hi> O bleſſed Lord, ſaith S. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe,</hi> they were not thy wounds,
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Ambr. de fide lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap</hi> 3. 2 Cor. 5.23.</note> but mine, that cauſed thy anguiſh. <hi>He knew no ſin,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>neither was there guile found in his mouth,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Eſay 53.9.</note> ſaith the Prophet.
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Maxim. Taur. Quadra. ſer.</hi> 1.</note> 
                              <hi>Eum nullum ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culauit delictu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> He was free from the leaſt blot of ſinne, figured in the Lambe without ſpot, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.5. And therfore he might boldly make that challenge to the faces of his greateſt aduerſaries,
<note place="margin">Iohn 8.46.</note> 
                              <hi>Which of you can rebuke mee of ſinne?</hi> Such was the innocency of our Sauiour,
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Ab omnibus accepit teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium, Iren. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>ca.</hi> 14. Luke 23.46.</note> as <hi>Iraeneus</hi> ſaith, that he had the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of all men, of all ſorts.</p>
                           <p>The Heauens were darkned, as being abaſhed to behold the Lord of glory ſo abaſed.
<note place="margin">Mat. 27.51.</note> The earth trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, as being afraid to beare thoſe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:177921:16"/>miſcreants, by whom innocency ſhould indure ſuch iniury. God from heauen proclaimed more then once,
<note place="margin">Mat. 3.17. &amp; 17.5.</note> 
                              <hi>This is my welbeloued Sonne, in whom I am well pleaſed.</hi> Infinite are the paſſages where men of all ſorts doe publiſh and applaud his inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency. The Angell <hi>Gabriel</hi> ſpake thus of him to the bleſſed Virgin, <hi>That holy thing that ſhall be borne of thee,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Luke 1.35.</note> 
                              <hi>ſhall be called the Sonne of God.</hi> The Deuils thus confeſſed him,
<note place="margin">Marke 1.24.</note> 
                              <hi>I know thee who thou art, euen the holy one of God.</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Iſay 53.11. 1 Iohn 2.2.</note> His friends, as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> the Prophet, and S. <hi>Iohn</hi> the Euangeliſt doe ſtile him, the <hi>iust,</hi> the <hi>righteous.</hi> His foes indeuoured by all the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines, that wit or malice deuiſe, to faſten ſome accuſation vpon him, but in vaine.
<note place="margin">Mat. 26.60.</note> His acquaintance did iuſtifie him: for ſo S. <hi>Peter,</hi> who was well acquainted with innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, obiected to the Iewes, <hi>You haue denied the holy one,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Acts 3.14.</note> 
                              <hi>&amp; the iust.</hi> Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers did acquite him, as <hi>Pilates</hi> wife
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:177921:16"/>in her monitory meſſage,
<note place="margin">Mat. 27.19.</note> 
                              <hi>Haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to doe with that iuſt man:</hi> and <hi>Pilate</hi> himſelfe profeſſed freely,
<note place="margin">Luke 23.4.</note> 
                              <hi>I finde no fault in this man.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Thus our bleſſed Sauiour had all the teſtimonies of his innocency, that heauen or earth, God or man, Angels or Diuels, friends or foes, acquaintance or ſtrangers, could yeeld. So that theſe infirmities and ſorrowes were ours; They were ours, yet his too; ours, as I ſaid, by way of appropriation, his by way of imputation, and expiation, as it is in the <hi>8. verſe</hi> of this Chapter,
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Fulgent. ad Thraſimund. lib.</hi> 3.</note> 
                              <hi>For the tranſgreſsion of my people was hee ſmitten. Quoniam peccata non habu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it propria, portare dignatus eſt aliena.</hi> He that had no ſinnes of his owne, vouchſafed to beare the ſinnes of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſaith <hi>Fulgentius.</hi> It was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that our Sauiour Chriſt ſhould be free from ſinne: for had he beene a ſinner, he could not haue beene a Sauiour. But now, <hi>He that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:177921:17"/>knew no ſinne, being made ſinne for vs, we thereby are made the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God in him,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Infirmitas &amp; mortalitas re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepta ſunt ad ſupplicium vt impenderentur ad precium. Leo de Reſur. ſer.</hi> 2. 1 Pet. 3.18.</note> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.23. As our infirmities were his puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſo are they our payment. <hi>My righteous ſeruant, ſaith the Lord, ſhall iuſtifie many, verſe 11.</hi> and therefore iuſtified, becauſe righteous. Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that of S. <hi>Peter, Chriſt ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for vs, the iust for the vniuſt, that he might bring vs to God.</hi> That hee might ſo bring vs to God, that wee might in this life be partakers of his grace, and of eternall glory in the life to come. Marchants vſe to ſhare in their paines, their gaines, their loſſes; but behold, Chriſt hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the paines, ſate downe by the loſſe, and yeeld; vs the gaine, the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit.</p>
                           <p>There is yet one little ſpring more to be opened, which hath not fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len into the ſtreame of our tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Chryſ. in Rom. hom.</hi> 31.</note> 
                              <hi>Si aurifuſorum pueri, &amp;c.</hi> If Goldfiners diligently ſeeke and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:177921:17"/>together the leaſt parcels of gold, I ſee no reaſon why we ſhould neglect the leaſt particle in this gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſentence. Here is the affix am, <hi>thoſe,</hi> and the accent <hi>Athnah,</hi> which, as Grammarians ſay,
<note place="margin">Lift vp the ſyllable.</note> doth <hi>attollere ſyllabam,</hi> teaching vs, that in the conſideration of our Sauiours ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, we ſhould raiſe vp our medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations to the higheſt pitch. Hee bare <hi>thoſe</hi> our infirmities; <hi>thoſe,</hi> which were exceeding preſſing; <hi>thoſe,</hi> which no tongue is able to expreſſe; for, <hi>Hic omnis lingua ſilet,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Barn. de quad. debit.</note> Euery tongue muſt be mute, as <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> ſaith. <hi>Thoſe,</hi> which all the men, and Angels, in heauen, and earth, were not able to beare; <hi>thoſe,</hi> which his humane nature could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue ſuſtained, had it not beene ſupported by his diuine power.
<note place="margin">Max. Taur.</note> 
                              <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titur vt homo, vincit vt Deus,</hi> though he ſuffer as man, he conquers as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="part">
                           <pb n="26" facs="tcp:177921:18"/>
                           <head>How, when, and where Chriſt bare theſe infirmities and ſorrowes.</head>
                           <p>HItherto wee haue opened the ſprings; now we will conſider the ſtreames.</p>
                           <p>In Hiſtories, the <hi>vbi, quando, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo,</hi> are very remarkable circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances. Therefore wee will briefly obſerue how, where, and when our Sauiour bare our infirmities, and carried our ſorrowes, in three eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall paſſages, that is, in his birth, life, and death. In his incarnation, his paſſion, his compaſſion.</p>
                           <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">1. In his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation. Phil. 2.7.</note> In his incarnation, hee was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly debaſed. <hi>Hee that was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall to God, made himſelfe of no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation,</hi> 
                              <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>, <hi>hee emptied himſelfe,</hi> as it were, of his excellent glory, when hee tooke vpon him our humane condition.
<note place="margin">Heb. 2.16.</note> 
                              <hi>Hee in no ſort tooke on him the nature of Angels,</hi>
                              <pb n="27" facs="tcp:177921:18"/>ſaith the Apoſtle, neither tooke hee the excellent eſtate of <hi>Adam.</hi> Hee tooke not vpon him the glorious e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of the Angels, for then, where had beene our greateſt comfort? He tooke not the excellent ſtate of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> for then, where had beene his abundant loue? But as S.
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Bern. in Epiph. ſer.</hi> 1.</note> 
                              <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, <hi>Suſcipiendo miſeriam, oſtendit miſericordiam,</hi> In taking our miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble condition, he doth manifeſt his mercy and compaſſion. <hi>He was made like vnto vs in all things, except ſinne, Heb. 4.15.</hi> And that indeed is iuſtly excepted; for, <hi>Aſſumpſit carnem,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Auguſt. in Pſal.</hi> 142. Rom. 8.3.</note> 
                              <hi>non iniquitatem,</hi> though hee tooke the ſimilitude of ſinnefull fleſh, yet hee tooke not the ſinne of the fleſh. As Phyſitions, by correcting their ingrediences, doe take away their malignant quality, and make the medicine healthfull: So the Holy Ghoſt in the conception of Chriſt, did vtterly take away the aduentiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous iniquity, &amp; ſanctifie the naturall
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:177921:19"/>infirmities, that no euill might cleaue vnto them.</p>
                           <p>Chriſt was ſubiect to infirmities both of body and ſoule: Not to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery particular infirmitie, as agues, aches, gouts and the like: For ſuch comming <hi>ex mala temperie, vel in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperantia,</hi> either by diſtemper, or an ill temperature, he was not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to them. He bare the naturall infirmities, not the perſonall. As <hi>Chryſostome</hi> ſaith, <hi>Quae communem naturam invaſerant,</hi> thoſe that are incident to the common nature of mankinde, thoſe he tooke. He was hungry, for ſo we reade <hi>Matth.</hi> 4. <hi>thirſtie, Iohn</hi> 19. <hi>ſleepie, Matth.</hi> 8. <hi>wearie, Iohn</hi> 4. In his ſoule he was ſubiect to feare,
<note place="margin">Math. 26. Marke 35.</note> anger, ſorrow and the like; He was abaſed in his kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ſome of them being ſinners, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterers, gentiles. Whereupon S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> cries out, <hi>O admirabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem natiuitatem,</hi> O admirable nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie.</p>
                           <pb n="29" facs="tcp:177921:19"/>
                           <p>At the time of his birth, he had a ſtable, in ſtead of a ſtately Palace; a manger, in ſtead of a cradle; the company of beaſts, in ſtead of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane and Angelicall attendance: So was he <hi>parvulus aetate, &amp; paupertate,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Auguſtin.</note> little both in age and eſtate.
<note place="margin">Luk. 2.21.</note> In his infancy he was ſubiect to that pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Sacrament of Circumciſion, and purſued from place to place by the hand of perſecution.
<note place="margin">Math. 2.13.</note> His whole life was dedicated to paines and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty. The open field was his houſe, the ground his bed, broyled fiſh his dyet; his iournies were laborious, his attendants men of meane quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Thus did he beare our infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in his Incarnation.</p>
                           <p n="2">2. Againe,
<note place="margin">2. In his compaſſion. <hi>Cyprian de Lapſis.</hi>
                              </note> in his tender compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion he carried our ſorrowes. For, as S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith, <hi>Maeroris pondera participat, &amp;c.</hi> He that hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion on another, partakes in the burden of his ſorrow. So did the Apoſtle when he ſaid, <hi>Who is weake,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">2. Cor. 11.23</note>
                              <pb n="30" facs="tcp:177921:20"/>
                              <hi>and I am not weake? who is offended and I burne not?</hi> And thus did our Sauiour, in commiſerating both the corporall, and ſpirituall infirmities of men. Thoſe that wanted food, and were ready to faint, he pittied: thoſe that were oppreſſed with ſickneſſe,
<note place="margin">Marke 8.1.</note> or poſſeſſed with euill ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits he condoled:
<note place="margin">Math. 8.</note> When <hi>he ſaw peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as ſheepe without a ſhepheard, He had compaſsion on them.</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Math. 9.</note>
                           </p>
                           <p>He is that good Samaritan, that had compaſſion on the wounded man,
<note place="margin">Luke 10.</note> powred wine, and oyle into his wounds, and bound them vp: And therefore was he ſent,
<note place="margin">Luke 4.18.</note> that he ſhould heale the broken hearted. If a man ſhould ſee a Chirurgion ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a plaiſter of his owne blood, for the curing of his patient, hee could not but wonder at it. And is not our Sauiours compaſſion admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable,
<note place="margin">Auguſtin.</note> 
                              <hi>Qui ex proprio, &amp; pretioſo ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine,</hi> Who of his owne pretious blood made a plaſter to cure the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:177921:20"/>wounds of our ſoules?
<note place="margin">Sueton. in vita Veſpaſ.</note> 
                              <hi>Suetonius</hi> writes of that good Emperour <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaſian, Iuſtis etiam ſupplicijs illachry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mauit, &amp; ingemuit:</hi> He was ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate a Prince, that hee was wont to ſigh and weepe, euen for them that were condignly puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Diuers ſtories doe mention ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny famous in this kinde. But what is all the compaſſion of men, yea of Saints and Angels, but <hi>gutta puſilla,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> a little drop of water, to the maine Ocean of our Sauiours compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? He was troubled in the ſpirit for treacherous <hi>Iudas;</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Iohn 13.21. Luke 19.4. Rom. 5.8. Luke 23.34.</note> wept for careleſſe Ieruſalem, ſhed his blood for his enemies, prayed for his cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell perſecutors.</p>
                           <p>Laſtly,
<note n="3" place="margin">In his Paſſion.</note> as our Sauiour did beare our infirmities, and carry our ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes in his compaſſion, ſo eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in his Paſſion. What ſtep did he take, what word did he ſpeake, what place came he to, where he left not <hi>Veſtigia dolorum,</hi> like the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:177921:21"/>print of the nailes in his hands and feete? When, in the garden of <hi>Geth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemane,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Math. 26.38.</note> he deſired the Diſciples to watch with him, he bare our infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities,
<note place="margin">Mark. 14.34.</note> and when he complained, that his ſoule was heauy vnto the death, hee carried our ſorrowes. When he prayed,
<note place="margin">Math. 26 39.</note> Father if it be poſſible <hi>let this cuppe paſſe,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Auguſt. in Pſal.</hi> 100.</note> 
                              <hi>(Quid illa vox niſi ſonus infirmitatis no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrae?)</hi> then he bare our infirmities, and when he had neede of an Angel to comfort him,
<note place="margin">Luke 22 43.</note> he carried our ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes. When he was bound, and ſo led to <hi>Annas</hi> and <hi>Caiphas,</hi> hee bare our infirmities, and when he ſpake to <hi>Iudas</hi> in that mournefull manner,
<note place="margin">Iohn 18.12.</note> 
                              <hi>betrayeſt thou the Sonne of man with a kiſſe,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Luke 12.48.</note> he carried our ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes. When the ſouldiers ſtrooke him with their reedes,
<note place="margin">Math. 27.30.</note> and ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged him with their rods, he bare our infirmities,
<note place="margin">Marke 14.64.</note> and when he was charged with blaſphemie, which his ſoule abhorred, he carried our
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:177921:21"/>ſorrowes. When <hi>Pilate,</hi> ſhewing him in that pittifull plight, ſaid;
<note place="margin">Iohn 19.5.</note> 
                              <hi>Ecce homo,</hi> Behold the man, <hi>he bare our infirmities,</hi> and when he heard that fearefull execration of the Iewes, <hi>His blood be vpon vs,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Math. 27.25.</note> 
                              <hi>and vpon our children, he carried our ſorrowes.</hi> But if we follow him to Mount <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uary,</hi> there ſhall we ſee this prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy moſt liuely accompliſhed. When his hands and his feet were pierced with the nailes, his ſide with the ſpeare, &amp; his head with the crowne of thornes; when the croſſe was his bed, the crowne of thornes his pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, gall and vineger his meate and drinke, ſcoffes and rayling his mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, he bare our infirmities; and when like a forlorne man, forſaken, as it were, of God and man, he cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out, <hi>My God, my God,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Math. 27.46.</note> 
                              <hi>why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> he both bare our infirmities, and carried our ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes. Here, his paſſion, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion met together, when his
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:177921:22"/>head hanged downe to kiſſe vs, His armes ſtretched out to embrace vs, His blood guſhed out to waſh vs, His ſoule and body were offered vp in ſacrifice for vs.
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Bernard. in Cant. Serm.</hi> 61.</note> 
                              <hi>Per vulnera pate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant viſcera,</hi> here through His ſide wounded with the ſpeare, you might behold His bowels of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion wounded with loue.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="part">
                           <head>Application.</head>
                           <p>AN ingenuous reader cannot goe ouer ſome rare and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſtory, but it will worke his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, in one kinde or another. Behold, the world neuer yeelded ſuch a memorable and admirable ſtory as this; It muſt needs be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our ſtupendious dulneſſe, if it doe not affect vs.</p>
                           <p>Firſt, who can conſider theſe things without admiration? Here is that, which may make both Saints and Angels to wonder, that
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:177921:22"/>one, who in his humane nature was deſcended of the blood royall of <hi>Iuda,</hi> and in his diuine, was Lord of heauen and earth, ſhould be thus deiected &amp; abaſed, and for whom? <hi>Pro vernaculo, imò pro vermiculo.</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Bernard. de quadrup. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bito.</note> For vs, who were the bond-ſlaues of ſinne and Satan, wormes and no men.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 8.</note> 
                              <hi>What is man O Lord that thou art ſo mindfull of him, or the Sonne of man that thou ſhouldeſt ſo regard him?</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Math. 8.21.</note> They that ſaw our Sauiours miracles, wondred, ſaying,
<note place="margin">Math. 8.21.</note> 
                              <hi>Who is this, that both windes and ſea obey him?</hi> But there was no ſuch cauſe to wonder at his actions of power: But rather, that he,
<note place="margin">Math. 28.18.</note> who <hi>had all power giuen him in heauen and earth,</hi> ſhould be ſubiect to weakeneſſe; and that by his infirmities and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, he ſhould obtaine a glorious victory, it is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>, beyond admiration.</p>
                           <p>Againe, this ſtory muſt needs yeeld comfort to a Chriſtian heart.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:177921:23"/>For he bare theſe infirmities, and carried theſe ſorrowes for our ſake, for our good; as it followeth in the next verſe; <hi>He was wounded for our tranſgreſsions, he was bruiſed for our iniquities, the chaſtiſement of our peace was vpon him, and by his ſtripes we are healed.</hi> Some write of the Pelican, that, her yong ones being dead, ſhe bathes them in her blood, and ſo reſtores them to life. How true that is, I know not: but ſure I am, that as S. <hi>Hierome</hi> ſaith, <hi>Chriſtus ſuo vulnere noſtra vulnera curauit.</hi> Chriſts wounds haue cured ours. For ſo ſaith the Prophet,
<note place="margin">Verſe 5.</note> 
                              <hi>By his ſtripes we are healed;</hi> his infirmities and weakeneſſe are our ſtrength; his ſorrowes our ioy, our comfort. He that bare our infirmities, and carried our ſorrowes, pitties vs, when infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities or ſorrowes doe ſeaze vpon vs.
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Cyprian Epi.</hi> 9.</note> 
                              <hi>Luctatur in nobis,</hi> he wreſtles for vs, with vs, in vs. He takes to heart the afflictions of his Church, and, as
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:177921:23"/>though he were wounded thorow her ſides, he cries out, <hi>Saul, Saul,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Act. 9.4.</note> 
                              <hi>why perſecuteſt thou me?</hi> He is ſenſible of our afflictions;
<note place="margin">Heb. 4.15.</note> For <hi>we haue not a high Prieſt, which cannot he touched with feeling of our infirmities;</hi> He might ſay, <hi>Non ignara mali miſeris ſuccurrere diſco.</hi> For ſo ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>In that Christ himſelfe hath ſuffered, being tempted, he is able to ſuccour them that are tempted, Hebr.</hi> 2.18.</p>
                           <p>Againe, who can read this Storie without indignation towards the Iewes, the cruell Actors in this dolefull Tragedie? He ſhed teares of pittie for them: they like pittileſſe wretches ſhed his precious blood. He turned their water into wine: they turned his wine into gall and vineger. He had an <hi>Ignoſce</hi> for them:
<note place="margin">Forgiue them <hi>Bern. Ser.</hi> 4. <hi>Hebd panoſ.</hi>
                              </note> they a <hi>Cruciſige</hi> for him. He gaue health to their ſicke, life to their dead they, in ſtead of requitall, took away his life, and put him to death.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:177921:24"/>May not I ſay in the Prophets wordes,
<note place="margin">Ier. 2.12.</note> 
                              <hi>O ye heauens be astonied at this, be affraide and vtterly confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded?</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Againe, who can read this Storie of our Sauiours paſſion, without compaſſion towards him?
<note place="margin">Zach. 12.10.</note> 
                              <hi>They ſhall looke vpon him, whom they haue pierced, and they ſhall lament for him,</hi> ſaith the Prophet. Can a man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, or heare, that his honourable friend hath been buffited, ſcourged, and put to extreme tortures for his ſake, and not be touched with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion?
<note place="margin">Luke 10.31.</note> Shall we be like the Prieſt, and the Leuite, that paſſed by the wounded man without pittie? Shall we ſay with thoſe wretches, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſhedding of our Sauiours innocent blood,
<note place="margin">Mat. 27.4.</note> 
                              <hi>Quid ad nos,</hi> What is that to vs? Then may he verie iuſtly take vp that expoſtulation, in the Lamentations of <hi>Ieremie,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Lam. 1.12.</note> 
                              <hi>Haue you no regard all you that paſſe by the way? Behold, was there euer ſorrow
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:177921:24"/>like my ſorrow?</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Thus farre, euen a meere naturall man may be mooued, and affected with this Storie; he may be ſtirred vp to admiration, entertaine conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, be moued to indignation, touched with compaſſion, &amp; when he hath done all this, he hath but viewed the couer of the Booke. There are other effects, which the meditation of this Storie muſt worke vpon our affections, and in our actions.</p>
                           <p n="1">1 This dolefull Storie muſt ſtrike our hearts with compunction, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which we cannot haue ſound conſolation. When the tender hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted women of Ieruſalem bewailed and lamented our Sauiour, as he went to be crucified, he ſaid vnto them, <hi>Daughters of Ieruſalem,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Luk. 23.28.</note> 
                              <hi>weepe not for me, but weepe for your ſelues, and for your children.</hi> So ſhould we bewaile our ſinfull condition, the cauſe of our Sauiours infirmities
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:177921:25"/>and ſorrowes.
<note place="margin">Luk. 23.48.</note> With ſhould, with thoſe good people that ſaw his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<note place="margin">Luk. 18.13.</note> ſtrike our breaſts, and ſay with the Publican, <hi>God be mercifull to me a ſinner.</hi>
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Chryſoſt. de Paſſio. Hom.</hi> 5.</note> For <hi>In ſpinis illis eum pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta nostra pungebant,</hi> Our ſinnes did pierce him in the Crowne of Thornes; and is it not reaſon, that our hearts ſhould be pierced with remorſe for our ſinnes?</p>
                           <p>It is not the weeping ouer a Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifixe, that Chriſt requires at our hands, but rather that <hi>we be crucified with him,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſpeakes, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. that is, as he interprets himſelfe,
<note place="margin">Gal. 5.24.</note> that <hi>we crucifie the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the fleſh, with the lustes thereof. Prote Dei filius ingulatus est,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Orig. Hom.</hi> 2. <hi>in Leuit.</hi>
                              </note> 
                              <hi>&amp; ite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum te peccare delectat?</hi> The Son of God was wounded for thee, and canſt thou yet delight in ſinne? He hath borne a heauie burthen of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, and ſorrowes, and ſhall we load him with new burthens? God forbid. For what were this, but with
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:177921:25"/>the Souldier to ſtrike him to the heart, and, as much as in vs lies,
<note place="margin">Heb. 6.</note> to crucifie him againe? The ſerious meditation of Chriſts paſſion, if we be not graceleſſe, will be a reſtraint of ſinne.</p>
                           <p n="2">
                              <hi>2</hi> Againe, as the Storie calls for our compunction,
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Auguſt. de Paſtore. cap.</hi> 5.</note> ſo doth it for our ſanctification. <hi>Haec omnia ille pro te, tu nihil pro illo,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Augustin?</hi> Hath Chriſt done, and indured all this for thee, and wilt thou doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for him? This were odious ingratitude. Take my <hi>yoke vpon you,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11. And it is verie reaſonable, that as he hath taken the yoke and burthen of puniſhment from our ſhoulders, ſo we ſhould willingly carie the burthen of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; eſpecially if we conſider the difference of theſe burthens. Ours laid vpon him was verie pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous, yea ſo heauie it was, that it made him ſweat vnder it. His is light as it is in the 11 of <hi>Mathew,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Mat. 11.33.</note>
                              <pb n="42" facs="tcp:177921:26"/>Yea,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.32.</note> ſo light, that a man, whoſe heart is ſanctified, may <hi>runne</hi> vnder it. And wee muſt take vp Chriſts burthen willingly, &amp; beare it cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, as he did ours. That we may ſay with him,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 40.7.</note> 
                              <hi>In the volume of thy booke it is written of me, that I ſhould doe thy will, I will doe it with all my heart.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="3">3. Againe, if it pleaſe God to lay vpon vs the burden of infirmities, ſorrowes, ſickneſſe, this may teach vs patience.
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Barn. paru. ſer. ſerm.</hi> 11.</note> 
                              <hi>Prius bibit potionem, quàm parauit ſuis.</hi> Chriſt hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to vs in the cup of ſorrows, and ſhall we think much to pledge him? His <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap> ſhould be our <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>, his patience in his paſſion muſt bee our inſtruction. And indeed, when we are oppreſſed with ſorrow, ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with paine, or caſt vpon the bed of our ſickneſſe, what meditation comparable to this, to lighten the burden of infirmities, and ſorrowes, and to ſweeten the bitterneſſe of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:177921:26"/>paine and anguiſh? Did my bleſſed Sauiour, who was holy and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, indure ſuch intollerable tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for my ſake? And ſhall I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine, or be impatient, when it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth God to afflict me? What are my greateſt afflictions to the paines of his paſſion? The time will come when paines or ſickneſſe are vpon vs, that we ſhall need this Cordiall, it ſhall be our happineſſe to haue it in a readineſſe.</p>
                           <p>To conclude, hath Chriſt borne our infirmities, and carried our ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes? This muſt preſſe vpon vs the Apoſtles exhortation,
<note place="margin">Gal. 6.2.</note> 
                              <hi>Beare yee one anothers burthens.</hi> For Chriſt is to vs both <hi>ſpeculum patiendi,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Bernard.</note> 
                              <hi>&amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patiendi,</hi> a looking-glaſſe and ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of Patience &amp; compaſſion. If we cannot cure, yet we ſhould condole the miſeries and infirmities of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 15.35.</note> Thus did <hi>Samuel</hi> bemoane the reiection of <hi>Saul.</hi> Thus did S. <hi>Paul</hi> bewaile the caſting away of
<note place="margin">Rom. 9.2.</note>
                              <pb n="44" facs="tcp:177921:27"/>the Iewes. And when he ſaw ſome walking in the way of damnation,
<note place="margin">Phil. 3.18.</note> hee could not ſpeake of it without teares.
<note place="margin">Coloſ. 3.12.</note> So let vs (as the Apoſtle ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts) <hi>put on the bowels of compaſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> that ſo we may ſhew our ſelues liuely members of our mercifull head Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
                           <p>Thus, if the meditation of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours bearing our infirmities and ſorrowes, doe worke in vs the grace of compunction, of ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, of obedience, patience, and compaſſion; then haue wee read it, heard it effectually: and we ſhall one day reape the fruit thereof moſt comfortably, when Chriſt ſhall returne,
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Non in infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, ſed in gloria &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtate. Bern. de Aduent. Ser.</hi> 6.</note> not ſubiect to infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and ſorrows, but cloathed with maieſty and glory, and ſhall giue vs poſſeſſion of that bleſſed habitation, where <hi>all teares ſhall be wiped from our eyes,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Reuel. 21.4.</note> and wee in ſtead of ſorrow and infirmity, ſhall enioy eternall ioy and felicity. Which the Lord
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:177921:27"/>for his mercies ſake, and for our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours ſake grant vs; to whom with the Holy Ghoſt, all honour and glory, maieſty and domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, be rendred and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </text>
               <text xml:lang="eng">
                  <front>
                     <div type="title_page">
                        <pb facs="tcp:177921:28"/>
                        <pb facs="tcp:177921:28"/>
                        <p>A CHECKE TO CVRIOSITY; AND <hi>The ſafeſt Seruice.</hi> TWO SERMONS preached at WHITEHALL, the one the 5. of <hi>May,</hi> the other the 12. 1622. <hi>BY</hi> IOHN DENISON Doctor of Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and one of his Maieſties Chaplaines.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by IOHN LEGATT, and are to be ſold by <hi>Iohn Budge,</hi> at the ſigne of the Greene Dragon in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1624.</p>
                     </div>
                  </front>
                  <body>
                     <div type="sermon">
                        <pb facs="tcp:177921:29"/>
                        <pb n="49" facs="tcp:177921:29"/>
                        <head>A CHECKE TO <hi>CVRIOSITY.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <epigraph>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>IOHN. 21.22.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>If I will that he tarry till I come, what is that to thee? follow thou me.</p>
                           </q>
                        </epigraph>
                        <p>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here was extraordinary intercourſe of loue and familiarity betweene <hi>Peter,</hi> a pillar of the Church, and <hi>Iohn</hi> the beloued Diſciple.</p>
                        <p>By him, <hi>Peter</hi> enquired concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Traitour. By his meanes hee got into the high Prieſts Hall.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:177921:30"/>With him, he ran to the Sepulchre. And by him he knew Chriſt at the ſea of <hi>Tiberias.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Therefore when our Sauiour had told <hi>Peter</hi> by an Allegory, that hee ſhould be ſubiect to martyrdome; <hi>Peter</hi> demanded of our Sauiour what <hi>Iohn</hi> ſhould doe? To whom our Sauiour anſwerd in theſe words that I haue read, <hi>If I will that he tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry till I come, &amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>In which I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue Chriſts <hi>Reprehenſion,</hi> and his <hi>Iniunction.</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Corrigit, &amp; dirigit.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>His <hi>Reprehenſion</hi> in theſe words, <hi>If I will that he tarry till I come, what is that to thee?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>His <hi>Iniunction</hi> in theſe, <hi>Follow thou me.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>In the <hi>Reprehenſion</hi> I note foure particulars;</p>
                        <p n="1">1. The ſoueraignety of Chriſts will, oppoſed to <hi>Peters</hi> curioſitie, <hi>If I will.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="2">2. Chriſts will applyed to an
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:177921:30"/>obiect, <hi>Iohns</hi> tarrying, <hi>If I will that he tarry.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="3">3. <hi>Iohns</hi> tarrying limited with a circumſtance of time; <hi>Till I come.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="4">4. <hi>Peters quid,</hi> checked with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other <hi>quid, what is that to thee?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Of theſe points briefly, and in order.</p>
                        <div type="part">
                           <head>If I will.</head>
                           <p n="1">1. THe vulgar Latine hath <hi>ſic vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo, ſo I will,</hi> but I may truely ſay, that that tranſlation is ſick. And I cannot but wonder at the Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts, who tie themſelues ſo ſtrictly to the ſame, that they ſwallow euen the groſſe errors of ignorant ſcribes. For they tranſlate it, <hi>ſo I will.</hi> But the learned Papiſts in tranſlating theſe words, doe generally correct and cenſure the vulgar Latine. <hi>Tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let</hi> giues two reaſons why it ſhould be <hi>ſi,</hi> not <hi>ſic,</hi> that is, it is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>, <hi>if,</hi> in the Greeke. And hee might with
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:177921:31"/>
                              <hi>Sa</hi> (another Ieſuite) haue ſaid it is ſo likewiſe in the Syriacke.
<note place="margin">Notat. in Bibl.</note>
                           </p>
                           <p n="2">2. If our Sauiour had ſaid <hi>ſic, ſo I will haue him remaine,</hi> the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on had beene anſwered, and no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doubt had remained concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his words.
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Mald. Omnes fere latinos ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices contami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nauit.</hi> And addes, It is ſo in all Greeke Copies, yea, that famous one in the <hi>Vatican. Ianſen. Concor. cap.</hi> 148.</note> 
                              <hi>Maldonat</hi> ſaith, <hi>That reading hath corrupted almoſt all Latine bookes.</hi> And <hi>Arboreus,</hi> a Doctor of <hi>Paris,</hi> ſpeakes yet more freely, <hi>The vulgar</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is harſh, vncouth, vnſauoury.</hi> Yea, the caſe is ſo cleare, that <hi>Ianſenius</hi> ſaith, <hi>Hee is peeuiſh that will contend for the vulgar tranſlation.</hi> Onely <hi>Michael</hi> the Maſter of the Popes Palace, will haue it to be <hi>ſic, ſo,</hi> becauſe it is ſo in the Miſſall corrected by <hi>Pius Quintus.</hi> But the reaſon is weake: for <hi>Sixtus Quintus,</hi> albeit hee tooke as great paines in correcting the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Latine,
<note place="margin">For, as I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, he hath left in his edition <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertit domum,</hi> for <hi>euerrit.</hi> Luke 15.8.</note> as <hi>Pius</hi> did in correcting the Miſſall, hath left ſome places of the houſe to be ſwept by others. <hi>Caietan</hi> (with whom <hi>Bellarmine</hi> alſo
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:177921:31"/>agreeth) ſayes reaſonably,
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Bellarm. de verbo Dei lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 11.</note> 
                              <hi>The Text ſhould not be changed for the ancient errors of ignorant writers.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>But if any will contend for this ancient vulgar error, let him abound in his owne ſenſe. We will proceed to the Soueraigntie of Chriſts will. <hi>If I will.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="part">
                           <head>The ſoueraigntie of Chriſts will.</head>
                           <p>NOw Chriſt is to be conſidered as God and man. As man,
<note place="margin">Iohn 5.30.</note> 
                              <hi>he came not to ſeeke his owne will, but the will of the Father, who ſent him.</hi> But as God, he hath a diuine will, and the ſame is either ſecret or reuealed. His ſecret will is his eternall pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and decree concerning all things.</p>
                           <p>This his ſecret will is <hi>abſolute,</hi> without dependance: he may will or nill whatſoeuer pleaſeth him. It is <hi>omnipotent</hi> without reſiſtance; for <hi>who hath reſiſted his will?</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Rom. 9.19.</note> it is <hi>free</hi>
                              <pb n="54" facs="tcp:177921:32"/>without coaction;
<note place="margin">Rom. 9.15.</note> For <hi>he will haue mercy on whom he will haue mercy.</hi> It is <hi>vniuerſall</hi> without limitation; For <hi>he beares rule,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Dan. 4.32. <hi>In maximis, minimis, &amp; contingentibus.</hi> Math. 10 29.</note> 
                              <hi>not only in the army of heauen, and the inhabitants of the earth,</hi> but ſo, that <hi>a ſparrow cannot fall on the ground without his will.</hi> It is exact without errors, as being a moſt perfect rule of righteouſnes. It cannot properly be ſaid, he wils it becauſe it is good: but rather, it is good becauſe he wils it. In a word, it is conſtant without altering, neither men, nor angels, nor deuils (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the deuilliſh poſitions of <hi>Vorſtius</hi>) can change it. They may ſooner remoue the earth from her center, or ſtay the motion of the heauens,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 46.10.</note> then alter it. <hi>My Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell ſhall ſtand, ſaith the Lord.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Now the reuealed will of Chriſt is that perfect rule of righteouſneſſe contained in the holy Scriptures. And to both theſe we muſt ſubmit our ſelues, but differently; to the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:177921:32"/>one <hi>pattendo,</hi> in being content with that which God doth: to the other <hi>faciendo,</hi> in doing what he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. For theſe two wils, are like two ſtreames riſing out of one head, the one running aboue, the other vnder the ground, and both falling into the Ocean of Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</p>
                           <p>The ſecret will, we muſt not be too buſie with, as ſome are in their deſperate diſputes about Predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.
<note place="margin">Deut. 29.29. <hi>Hieron. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>aduerſ. Pelag</hi>
                              </note> For <hi>Secret things belong to the Lord. Voluntas Dei non diſcuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enda, ſed patienda;</hi> This will of God is not to be ſearched, but to be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, ſaith <hi>S. Hierome.</hi> And this was <hi>Peters</hi> fault: He was too in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitiue after that which was loc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vp in our Sauiours breſt, and was therefore iuſtly checked. Yet euen to this will we muſt ſubſcribe in ſuffering patiently, and entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thankfully whatſoeuer it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the Lord to doe. As <hi>Ely,</hi> when
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:177921:33"/>he had heard that dolefull doome denounced by God againſt his houſe,
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 3.18.</note> ſaid, <hi>It is the Lord, let him doe what ſeemeth him good.</hi> Thus King <hi>Dauid,</hi> when he went forth againſt <hi>Abſolon,</hi> (not knowing what might be the iſſue of that warre,) ſet vp his reſt.
<note place="margin">2. Sam. 15.25.</note> 
                              <hi>If I ſhall finde fauour in the eyes of the Lord, he will bring me againe and ſhew mee both the Arke and the Tabernacle thereof: But if he thus ſay, I haue no delight in thee, Behold here am I, let him doe to me as ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth good in his eyes.</hi> And our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sauiour, when he was in the greateſt agony that euer ſeazed on the ſoule of man, and dranke the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt cuppe that euer was taſted, ſubmitted himſelfe in this manner: <hi>O Father,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Math. 26.42.</note> 
                              <hi>If this cuppe cannot paſſe, except I drinke it, thy will be done.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Againe, as we muſt ſubmit our ſelues to the ſecret will of Chriſt in ſuffering what he inflicts; ſo muſt we to the reuealed, in doing what
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:177921:33"/>he commands. And as it ſhall bee our wiſedome to know this reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led will of God (according to that in the 5. to the Epheſians:
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.17.</note> 
                              <hi>Bee not vnwiſe, but vnderſtand what the will of the Lord is</hi>) ſo ſhall it be our hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe to doe it, as our Sauiour ſaith in the 13. of <hi>Iohn.</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Ioh. 13.17.</note> 
                              <hi>If you know theſe things, bleſſed are you if you doe them.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>This reuealed will is called <hi>the voyce of God,</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.22. And that very fitly: For as the echo reſounds to the vnice, ſo muſt we, both in our affections and actions, be anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the will of God. In our affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 27.8.</note> as when the Lord ſaid to <hi>Dauid: Seeke my face, Dauids heart anſwered like an echo, Lord I will ſeeke thy face.</hi> In our actions like <hi>Noah,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Gen. 6.22.</note> 
                              <hi>Who did according to all that God commanded him, euen ſo did he.</hi> And this we ſhall the more readily doe, if we conſider the corrupt current of our owne wils, and the abſolute
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:177921:34"/>perfection of Almightie Gods.</p>
                           <p>That is a moſt arrogant Romiſh Extrauagant, which yeelds that ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigntie to the Pope, that belongs only to God, <hi>In his quae vellent, ijs eſſe pro lege voluntatem.</hi> Though the Popes be ignorant, or diſſolute, and ſtand for a law. And their actions, though neuer ſo abſurd or impious, are not ſubiect to controule, that a man ſhould ſay, <hi>Domine cur hoc fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis,</hi> Sir why doe you thus? But a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaunt to this <hi>Luciferian</hi> arrogancie; it is the will of God to which wee muſt thus neceſſarily, and abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubſcribe. And the more prompt our obedience, the more doe we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble the holy Angels. For <hi>with the bleſſed Angels,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>In caeleſti An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelorum curia Dei voluntas Lex eſt. Auguſt de Ciuitat. Dei. z.</hi> 19. Pſal. 103.20.</note> 
                              <hi>Gods will is a law in the Court of heauen,</hi> as S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith. And their <hi>elogium</hi> is in the 103. Pſalme; <hi>Ye Angels that doe his commandement, in obeying the voyce of his word.</hi> Yea herein we ſhall imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate our bleſſed Sauiour, who in his
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:177921:34"/>paſſion prayed; <hi>Not as I will,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Math. 26.39.</note> 
                              <hi>but as thou wilt:</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Ioh. 4.34.</note> And in his actions ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted it <hi>his meate and drinke to doe the will of his Father.</hi> And if we thus ioyne with our bleſſed Sauiour and his holy Angels in will and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, we ſhall hereafter be ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with them in a bleſſed habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; according to that of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, in the 7. of Matthew.
<note place="margin">Math. 7.21.</note> 
                              <hi>He ſhall enter into the kingdome of heauen, that doth the will of my Father which is in heauen.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="part">
                           <head>Chriſts will applyed to an obiect.</head>
                           <p n="2">2. <hi>IF I will that he tarry.</hi> This ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying hath not reference to <hi>Iohns</hi> tarying in the place where he was, but his remaining in the ſtate of life which he enioyed; as the ſame phraſe is elſewhere vſed.
<note place="margin">
                                 <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                                    <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                                 </gap>. 1. Cor. 15.6. Whereof ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny remaine.</note> 
                              <hi>Peter</hi> vnderſtood by our Sauiours words that he muſt die by the hand of vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and he would know whether
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:177921:35"/>the thread of <hi>Iohns</hi> life ſhould be cut off in that manner. But our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour intimates the contrary, ſaying, if <hi>I will that he tarry;</hi> that is, If I will that hee remaine aliue. In which manner of ſpeech he ſets forth the vanitie of this preſent life, as being tranſitory, and only a temporary tarrying. And ſo doth <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeake of it.
<note place="margin">Iob. 14.1.</note> 
                              <hi>Man that is borne of a woman is of ſhort continuance, he ſhootes vp like a flower, and is cut downe, he vaniſheth like a ſhadow, and continueth not.</hi> And if there be any continuing, it is limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with a <hi>Donec.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>We are all tenants at will. And this world is to vs but <hi>diuerticulum,</hi> an Inne to hoſte at, not a ſetled ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation to reſt at: as euen the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then haue called it.
<note place="margin">Heb. 13.14.</note> 
                              <hi>Hic non habemus permanentem ciuitatem:</hi> Here wee haue no abiding Citie. This did king <hi>Dauid</hi> acknowledge ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly,
<note place="margin">1 Chron. 29.15.</note> in the height of his honour and happineſſe. <hi>Wee are ſtrangers
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:177921:35"/>(ſaith he) and ſoiourners, our daies are as a ſhadow, there is no abiding.</hi> Some tarry here but a while, like <hi>Dauids</hi> infant,
<note place="margin">2 Sam. 12.18.</note> 
                              <hi>that dyed the ſeauenth day;</hi> ſome not ſo long. <hi>Nec dum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troitus, iam exitus,</hi> as S. <hi>Hierome</hi> ſaies;
<note place="margin">Pliny.</note> they liue not to enioy the light whileſt the ſnuffe of a candle makes an abortiue birth. Some liue longer, like the Shunamites childe.
<note place="margin">2 Reg. 4.</note> Some till they haue attained to their full ſtrength,
<note place="margin">Iob 21.23.</note> and <hi>their bones are full of marrow,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">2 Sam. 19.</note> Some euen to a decrepit eſtate, like old <hi>Barzillai.</hi> Yet he that tarryeth longeſt (of which there are feweſt) hath but a time of tarrying. Though Comets differ from one another in brightneſſe, and ſome ſhine longer then others, yet at laſt they all vaniſh: So, albeit in the fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament of this preſent world, ſome attaine to higher degrees of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and ſome liue longer then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, yet there is a vaniſhing of both. <hi>The faſhion of this world paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:177921:36"/>away,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.31.</note> ſaith the Apoſtle. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when <hi>Conſtantius</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour asked <hi>Hormiſda</hi> the famous Architect, what hee thought of <hi>Rome,</hi> it being ſuch a goodly Citie, he returned him little more then this anſwer:
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Platina in vita Faelicis.</hi> 2.</note> 
                              <hi>Didici quoque ibi ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines mori,</hi> This I haue obſerued, that men die there as well as in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places.</p>
                           <p>Euerie ſublunarie <hi>creature grones vnder the bondage of corruption,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Rom 8.22.</note> and hath ſome thing in it, that works the decay of it. The Yron hath ruſt, the tree the worme, the ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ker; &amp; ſo hath man his depraued humours, beſides thoſe externall accidents which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breuiate his daies. <hi>This life is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall conſumption.</hi>
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Aul. Gell. Noct. Attic.</hi> 11.2.</note> Therefore <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Cato</hi> was wont to compare a man to Yron, <hi>Si exerceas conteritur,</hi> If you vſe it, you waſt it: if not, yet the ruſt conſumes it. And I may ſay with that deuout Father, <hi>Dum vobis hodie loquor,</hi> Euen this day whileſt I
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:177921:36"/>am ſpeaking to you, the Lampe of my life waſteth, and whether I ſhall tarie to finiſh what I haue prepared I know not. Oh how great is the folly of theſe, who would build them euerlaſting habitations in this vale of miſerie;
<note place="margin">Pſalm. 49.11.</note> 
                              <hi>And thinke their houſes ſhall continue for euer, &amp; from generation to generation?</hi> Behold the <hi>Pſalmists</hi> cenſure:
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Bern. de conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. ad Eugen. lib.</hi> 2.</note> 
                              <hi>This their way vttereth their fooliſhneſſe. Per ina nem ſollicitudinem in aliena migrant ſaecula, non profutura, imo nec futura.</hi> Their care extendes to other ages, which ſhall neither yeeld benefit, no, nor being. The yeeres they rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon of,
<note place="margin">The great yeere. The great folly. <hi>Zanch.</hi> Luk. 12.19.</note> are like the Philoſophers <hi>Annus maximus,</hi> which one verie iuſtly calls <hi>Maximam ſtultitiam.</hi> As that rich man, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. did, who ſaid to himſelfe, <hi>Soule thou hast goods in ſtore for many yeeres,</hi> and therefore receaued that iuſt anſwer by the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall Oracle, <hi>Thou foole, this night ſhall they take away thy Soule.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <pb n="64" facs="tcp:177921:37"/>
                           <p>Mens hope of long life is <hi>Fluxa &amp; falſa,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Aug. in Pſ.</hi> 53.</note> falſe and floting, as S. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> ſaid.
<note place="margin">Pſ. 90.12.</note> Therefore <hi>Moſes</hi> prayed, <hi>Teach vs oh Lord to number our daies, that we may apply our hearts vnto wiſdome.</hi> And how ſhould we number them? Not like that fooliſh Arithmetician, the rich man, by many yeeres;
<note place="margin">
                                 <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                                    <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                                 </gap> Iob 14.1.</note> but as <hi>Iob</hi> doth (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the words in the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall) by a few ſhort daies. Why ſhould any one make reckoning of this tarying;
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Baſil. Hexam. Hom.</hi> 5.</note> when as <hi>Vna nox, vna febris, vna pleuritis,</hi> One nights ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, one poore feuer, or pleuriſie may end this life?
<note place="margin">Eccl. 1.4.</note> 
                              <hi>One generation paſſeth, and another ſucceedeth,</hi> as <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> faith. How many carcaſes of demoliſhed Cities may we ſee, wherein multitudes of people inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited? How many worlds of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, hauing taried here for a while, are ſwept away by death, like the gathering Hoſte of <hi>Dan?</hi> What greater folly therefore, then to be
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:177921:37"/>prodigall in meaſuring that time which is not in our diſpoſing? How much better ſhall we doe? How much happier ſhall we be, if we be carefull to employ our pittance fruitfully, to the glorie of God, and the furtherance of our happie ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt in the day of the Lord?</p>
                           <p>The Heathen Philoſopher verie worthily taxed this folly,
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Seneca Epi.</hi> 22.</note> that <hi>Moſt men deſire to liue long, few haue care to liue well; Cum omnibus contingat bene viuere, nulli diu;</hi> When it is in euerie mans power to liue well, but in no mans to liue long.
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Vt aliquid effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciat quod vita dignum ſit. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctan. de Opif. Dei cap.</hi> 4.</note> A good man may deſire to liue long, but it muſt be, that he may doe good. For therefore indeed (ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>) <hi>Deus facit viuere vt illi viuamus,</hi> Our liues are giuen vs of God, that they ſhould be ſpent in his ſeruice, and to his glorie: Otherwiſe our <hi>Morari,</hi> our tarying, is but a <hi>Morari</hi> with a long ſyllable as <hi>Nero</hi> ſpake in <hi>Suetonius,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Suet in Neron. cap.</hi> 33.</note> Our <hi>daies</hi> are ſpent <hi>foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhly,</hi>
                              <pb n="66" facs="tcp:177921:38"/>and ſhall end <hi>miſerably.</hi> To conclude this point; Foraſmuch as here is no long tarying, why ſhould we dote vpon this tranſitorie life? <hi>Is here no abiding Citie? Let vs looke for one to come,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.1.</note> 
                              <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. <hi>Shall theſe earthly tabernacles of ours be destroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? Let vs deſire that building, which is eternall in the Heauens.</hi> Will the time come that all earthly King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes ſhall haue their periods, and <hi>Chriſt himſelfe deliuer vp his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to the Father?</hi>
                              <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.24.</note> Let vs then aſpire to that heauenly Kingdome, <hi>that can neuer be ſhaken.</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Heb. 12.28.</note> Here indeed is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>, a tarying, but it is with a <hi>donec,</hi> for a ſhort time; but there are <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>, conſtant manſions, as our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſpeakes,
<note place="margin">Luk. 16.9. 1. Theſ. 4.17.</note> 
                              <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.1. Yea <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>, euerlaſting habitations. There <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>, we ſhall euer be with the Lord; in whoſe preſence is the fulneſſe of ioy,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 16.</note> and at whoſe right hand are pleaſures for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. And (that I may end this
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:177921:38"/>point with S.
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>De ciuitate Dei lib.</hi> 22. <hi>cap.</hi> 30.</note> 
                              <hi>Auguſtins</hi> words) <hi>Quis alius noſter est finis, niſi perue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nire ad regnum, cuius nullus est finis?</hi> To what end doe we liue, but, that after our tarying here, we may come to that Kingdome that ſhall neuer end?</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="part">
                           <head>Iohns tarying limited.</head>
                           <p n="3">3. <hi>TIll I come.</hi> I may ſay for the meaning of theſe words, <hi>Quot homines tot ſententiae,</hi> So many men, ſo many ſeuerall opinions. Some by this <hi>donec, till I come,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand Chriſts comming at the end of the world. And that hath beene the ground of a vulgar, but ſenſeleſſe error; Namely, that <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Euangelist</hi> is yet aliue,
<note place="margin">Beda de te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pore.</note> whereas he dyed in peace, the 98 yeere of his life at Epheſus. Yea ſome there haue beene, who, vnder the colour of this expoſition, haue taken vpon them the perſon of S. <hi>Iohn;</hi> As that
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:177921:39"/>late Impoſtor of France did,
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Beza refert Annot. in Ioh.</hi> 21.</note> and was therefore iuſtly burned at To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſe. Some vnderſtand it of Chriſts comming to <hi>Iohn,</hi> by ſummoning him to his death; which if it be meant of death in generall, without any difference between the manner and meanes of ſuch death, muſt needs be a groundleſſe conſtruction. For ſo Chriſt came to all his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, whereas this comming implies ſomething more then ordinarie. Diuers other conceites there are concerning this comming of Chriſt, which are not worthy the repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, much leſſe the refuting. I may ſay of this queſtion,
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Auguſt. in Ioh. trac.</hi> 46.</note> as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeakes vpon the like; <hi>I will in this deepe queſtion deliuer what to me ſeemes right, reſeruing to euerie one what likes him beſt.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Now for clearing of this place other Scriptures will yeeld vs light. They are like the Cherubims,
<note place="margin">Exod. 25.20.</note> 
                              <hi>that looked one on another, Exod.</hi> 25. And
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:177921:39"/>
                              <hi>thoſe that had their wings ioyned one in another, Ezech.</hi> 1.
<note place="margin">Ezech. 1.9.</note> They are like ſo many ſweet Inſtruments according in one note of truth.</p>
                           <p>S.
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Bernard. de Aduent. ſer.</hi> 3.</note> 
                              <hi>Bernard</hi> hath a diſtinction of a threefold comming of Chriſt men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the Scriptures; The firſt, <hi>ad homines,</hi> to men, in his incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; The ſecond, <hi>in homines,</hi> into men, at their conuerſion; The third, <hi>contra homines,</hi> againſt men, at the worlds diſſolution. The firſt of theſe was in <hi>infirmitie,</hi> the ſecond in <hi>power and ſpirit,</hi> the third ſhall be in <hi>maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie and glorie.</hi> Now two of theſe are his comming in perſon, that is at his Incarnation, &amp; the day of Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; the third is his comming in power, that is his powerfull worke in the promulgation of the Goſpel, and the conuerſion of ſinners; And of this his third comming our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſpeakes to <hi>Peter.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>That place in the ſixteenth of Saint <hi>Mathew,</hi> is,
<note place="margin">Mat. 16.28.</note> in my opinion a
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:177921:40"/>liuely parallell to this. <hi>Verely, there are ſome ſtanding here, which ſhall not tast of death, till they haue ſeene the Son of Man come in his Kingdome.</hi> For what is this, <hi>he ſhall tarie,</hi> but that, <hi>he ſhall not taſt of death?</hi> What is this <hi>Donec,</hi> till I come, but that <hi>comming of the Son of Man in his Kingdome?</hi> And what is that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, but the powerfull effects of the Goſpel? as it is in the ſame Euangeliſt,
<note place="margin">Mat. 10.7. &amp; 12.28.</note> where our Sauiour ſaith <hi>The Kingdome of God is come to you:</hi> As the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> alſo explaines it,
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.16.</note> 
                              <hi>We opened to you the power and comming</hi> (that is the powerfull comming) <hi>of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> True it is, that then Chriſt came powerfully in his Doctrine and Myracles; But afterwards more powerfully, and plentifully in the Miniſterie of the Apoſtles, as will be euident, if we conſider theſe three circumſtances</p>
                           <p n="1">1. The firſt is the effuſion of gifts
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:177921:40"/>
                              <hi>poured out</hi> vpon the Apoſtles at the feaſt of Pentecoſt.
<note place="margin">Act. 2.33. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                                    <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                                 </gap>. Luke 24.49. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                                    <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                                 </gap>. 2. Iudg. 6.34. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                                    <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                                 </gap> Rom. 15.19.</note> For then they were <hi>indued with power from on high.</hi> Euen <hi>cloathed with the Spirit of power,</hi> as it is ſaid of <hi>Gideon</hi> in the ſixt of the Iudges. They had <hi>the power of ſignes and wonders.</hi> They had that powerful Apoſtolicall rod, wherewith Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſtrooke <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias</hi> the diſſembler,
<note place="margin">Acts 5.5. Act. 13.11.</note> and <hi>Paul Ely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> the ſorcerer.</p>
                           <p n="2">2. The ample promulgation of the Goſpel. For as <hi>Noes</hi> ſonnes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed themſelues for the peopling of a new world; ſo did the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles for the planting of a new word. <hi>Euſebius</hi> writes,
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Euſeb. hiſt.</hi> Eccleſ. 2.3.</note> that about the end of <hi>Tyberius</hi> raigne, the Goſpel through Gods gracious bleſſing, <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi vniuerſo veluti ſolaris quidam ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius illuxit,</hi> Did ſhine like a bright Sun-beame to all the world. Saint Paul <hi>cauſed the Goſpel to ſound out from Ieruſalem to Illyricum.</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Rom. 15.18.</note>
                              <note place="margin">Chryſoſtome.</note> And if one Apoſtle did ſo much in one part
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:177921:41"/>of the world, what may we thinke of all the reſt? Surely that which we reade in the tenth of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes,
<note place="margin">Rom. 10.18.</note> 
                              <hi>Their ſound went forth to all the earth, and their words to the end of the world,</hi> and that propheticall promiſe was now fulfilled;
<note place="margin">Math. 10.23.</note> 
                              <hi>Yee ſhall not goe ouer all the Cities of Iſrael, till the Sonne of man be come.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="3">3. The effectuall and happie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion of the world, by that mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of the Apoſtles, was very wonderfull. <hi>Peters</hi> draught was great,
<note place="margin">Iohn 21.11.</note> 
                              <hi>when he tooke</hi> 153. <hi>fiſhes;</hi> But that greater, when, being made a fiſher of men,
<note place="margin">Acts 2.41.</note> 
                              <hi>He in one day conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> 3000. <hi>ſonles.</hi> Now the Curtaines of the Church were ſpread out, and her tents inlarged exceedingly. So that whereas ſhee was before like <hi>Gideons</hi> fleece, ſhe became now like <hi>Gideons</hi> floore, inlarged and watered abundantly with the dew of the Goſpel.
<note place="margin">Euſeb. quo ſupra.</note> Inſomuch that as <hi>Euſebius</hi> writes, <hi>many Cities and Villages,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:177921:41"/>were veluti refertae frugum areae,</hi> as it were threſhing floores full of corne. Now, if the Goſpel flouriſhed, and the Church increaſed thus in the daies of <hi>Tiberius,</hi> how much more in the daies of <hi>Traian,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Baron. tom.</hi> 1. <hi>ad annum</hi> 69. <hi>nu.</hi> 34.</note> which was 60. yeares after, All which Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> tarryed to ſee? Thus in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the powerfull gifts of the ſpirit, the ample promulgation of the Goſpel, and the wonderfull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion of the world, we may well ſay that Chriſt Ieſus then came, and came in his kingdome, his ſcepter being ſo gloriouſly aduanced.</p>
                           <p>But it concernes vs much, by way of application, to conſider more thoroughly of this comming in <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines,</hi> into men.</p>
                           <p>The comming of our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour at the time of his birth, was apparant. For,
<note place="margin">Iohn 1.14.</note> 
                              <hi>The word was made fleſh, and dwelt among vs,</hi> (<hi>and</hi> men <hi>ſaw the glory thereof, as the glory of the only begotten Son of the Father</hi>)
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:177921:42"/>
                              <hi>full of grace and truth.</hi> And ſuch will his comming to iudgement be: For <hi>he will come in flaming fire,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 1.8.</note> 
                              <hi>and render vengeance to the ignorant, and diſobedient.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Thoſe two commings of Chriſt are manifeſt, and of them men are ſenſible; But this middle comming is <hi>Ocultus &amp; ſpiritualis,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Bernard de Aduent. Ser.</hi> 3.</note> Secret and ſpirituall, and few are truly appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſiue of it. Yet they only ſhall haue comfort of his comming in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie, and at his comming in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, who haue experience of his comming in grace.
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.9.</note> For <hi>if any man hath not the Spirit of Chriſt, the ſame is none of his.</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Bernard ibid.</note> 
                              <hi>Aduentus iſte medius eſt via per quam veniatur ad vlti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum:</hi> This middle comming is the way by the which we come happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the laſt.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Behold</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>I ſtand at the doore,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Reuel. 3.20.</note> 
                              <hi>and knocke.</hi> He ſtands at the doore of mens hearts, and knockes with two eſpeciall hammers, the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:177921:42"/>Miniſtery of the word, and the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his bleſſed ſpirit, but is oft neglected, repelled. As it is ſaid of his comming in perſon,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.11.</note> 
                              <hi>He came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his owne, but his owne receiued him not:</hi> ſo is it true of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in power, that hee comes to many by outward meanes, to whom he comes not by effectuall grace. Therfore it is neceſſary to examine how Chriſt is come to vs. Yea e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one ſhould, in this caſe, be <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſus explorator,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Bernard in Cant. Serm.</hi> 74.</note> A curious and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent examiner (as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpeakes.) According to that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Brooue your ſelues,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">2. Cor. 13.5.</note> 
                              <hi>examine your ſelues, know you not that Chriſt is in you, except you be reprobates?</hi> Euery one will acknowledge,
<note place="margin">Acts 17.28.</note> that <hi>in him we liue, and mooue, and haue our being:</hi> But then only are we hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie, when we can ſay,
<note place="margin">Gal. 2.20.</note> that <hi>Christ liues in vs.</hi> Therefore, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> prayes,
<note place="margin">Eph. 3.20.</note> that <hi>he may know the vertue of Chriſts reſurrection;</hi> ſo we ſhould
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:177921:43"/>pray, that we may know the power of this his comming.</p>
                           <p>But <hi>Vnde adeſſe norim?</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Bernard. quo ſupra.</note> ſaith S. <hi>Bernard,</hi> How ſhall I know that he is come? And ſurely this is a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, and waightie queſtion. For re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution whereof, we are to take notice, that where Chriſt comes, he comes as a <hi>Conquerour.</hi> There will be <hi>fuga vitiorum,</hi> Sinne will be put to flight:
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Bernard. Potentia pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cati imminuta, &amp;c. Chryſoſt. Orat.</hi> 8. Reu. 1.16. Heb. 4.12.</note> At leaſt the ſtrength of ſinne will be abated, and the power of Satan quelled. For Chriſt hath his <hi>two edged ſword,</hi> which is liuely and mightie in operation, and thoſe weapons, that can caſt downe the ſtrongeſt holds. Where he comes in ſpirit, and power, Satans forts and bariquadoes muſt needs be bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered. Can Dagon ſtand before the Arke? or Belial before Chriſt? Thoſe therefore that finde in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues the power of ſinne abated, may conclude with comfort, that Chriſt is come. And contrarily,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:177921:43"/>where the forts of Satan ſtand vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>battered, and the force of ſinne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines, Chriſt is not come effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally.</p>
                           <p>Againe, where Chriſt comes powerfully as a Conquerour, hee makes his reſidence gratiouſly as a King, <hi>Vt nos ei ſubijciamur,</hi> That we,
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Nazianz de fil. Orat.</hi> 5.</note> as good ſubiects, may ſerue and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey him. He will not ſuffer ſinne to raigne, where he hath his reſidence. So ſaith the Apoſtle,
<note place="margin">Rom. 6.14.</note> 
                              <hi>Sinne ſhall not haue dominion ouer you, for you are not vnder the law, but vnder grace.</hi> We cannot be totally free from ſin, whileſt we liue in this vale of miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; but, if Chriſt be in vs, he will ſuppreſſe the power of it. For, can a rebell ſtand before the face of a potent Prince? Where Chriſt raignes as King, his ſubiects will be ready to be ruled by his ſcepter, and they ſtand in awe of his ſword of Iuſtice. A good ſubiect will <hi>take heed to the mouth of the King.</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 8.2.</note> And
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:177921:44"/>can he be a good ſubiect to Chriſt, the King of Kings, which will not bee guided by his word? Thoſe therefore that ſay in their hearts, <hi>Let vs breake their bonds aſunder,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Pſalme 2.3.</note> 
                              <hi>and caſt away their cords from vs,</hi> doe ſhew themſelues, not ſubiects, but rebels: They haue not yet entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Chriſt; and their doome is fearefull, as it is pronounced, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.
<note place="margin">Luke 19.27.</note> 
                              <hi>Thoſe mine enemies, which would not that I ſhould raigne ouer them, bring them, and ſlay them before my face.</hi> We pray daily, Thy kingdome come,
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Auguſtine Hom.</hi> 42.</note> 
                              <hi>Et veniet ſi volumus:</hi> It will come, if we our ſelues be willing; If we be contented to be ruled by the ſpirit of Chriſt, directed by his word, and tender vnto him the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of cheerefull obedience, then is this King of glory come gratiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to vs,
<note place="margin">Luke 17.21.</note> and <hi>the kingdome of God is within vs.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Againe, where Chriſt comes ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually, he comes as a gracious be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactor,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:177921:44"/>
                              <hi>He comes not empty handed.</hi>
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Bern. in Cant. ſerm.</hi> 74. <hi>Auguſt. de Trinit. &amp; v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit. cap.</hi> 11.</note> 
                              <hi>Quid eſt venire, niſi gratiam ſuam nobis conferre?</hi> What is this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt to vs, but the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring of his grace?
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.10.</note> 
                              <hi>And his grace in vs will not be in vaine,</hi> but will ſtirre vs vp to the practiſe of all holy duties. <hi>Si Chriſtus in corde ſit,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Orig in Rom.</hi> 14.</note> 
                              <hi>nobis diem facit,</hi> If Chriſt be entertained into our hearts, he,
<note place="margin">Mal. 42.</note> being <hi>Sol iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae, the Sunne of righteouſneſſe,</hi> will expell the darkneſſe of errour, and cauſe the light of knowledge to ſhine into our ſoules. For,
<note place="margin">Luke 1.78.</note> he <hi>came to giue light to them that ſit in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and to guide our feet into the way of peace.</hi> Hee is the Prince of peace,
<note place="margin">Rom. 5.1.</note> 
                              <hi>and through him we haue peace with God.</hi> If our ſoules bee woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with remorſe, he brings his cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dials to comfort vs, and his ſuppling balmes to cure vs.
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Hieron. in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ.</hi> 7.</note> He is <hi>magister medicorum,</hi> the great Phyſition, and pittifull Chyrurgion. His cures are ſtrange, he heales the broken hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted:
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:177921:45"/>And how?
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Orig. in Leuit. hom.</hi> 8.</note> 
                              <hi>Non herbarum ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis, ſed verborum Sacramentis,</hi> hee cures them by ſpeaking peace to their ſoules. That which was loſt by <hi>Adam,</hi> is reſtored by him; and that image which was defaced, is renued by him.
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Bern. in Cant. ſerm</hi> 74. <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pergefacit dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mientem ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam, &amp;c.</hi>
                              </note> S. <hi>Bernard</hi> reckons vp a large Catalogue of comforts, and benefits, that we receiue by the comming of this gracious benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor; <hi>Hee awakens the drouſie ſoule, and mollifies the ſtonie heart; he plucks vp vice, and plants vertue; hee caſts downe the wals of iniquity, and builds vs vp in grace; he waters that which is thirſty, enlightens that which is darke, opens that which is locked vp, and kindles that which is cold.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Now, to conclude this point: hath Chriſt enlightened vs with ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing knowledge, ſpoken peace to our ſoules, awaked vs from drouſie ſecurity, mollified our hearts, plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted grace in our ſoules, changed our affections, made vs zealous of his
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:177921:45"/>glory? then may wee ſay confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and comfortably, with that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Martyr, <hi>Hee is come, he is come.</hi> And indeed no comfort on earth like vnto this, <hi>Beatus apud quem man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionem facis Domine Ieſu, O Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> (ſaith S.
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Bern. de Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent. ſerm.</hi> 3.</note> 
                              <hi>Bernard</hi>) <hi>happie is the man with whom thou takeſt vp thy dwelling.</hi> Let vs therefore be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, not onely to entertaine,
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Nobilem ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitem Bern.</hi> It is ſaid they conſtrained him. Luke 24.29. Iohn 14.23.</note> but alſo to retaine this noble gueſt. Let vs make the Diſciples importunate ſuite to him, in <hi>Luk. 24. Mane nobiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum,</hi> abide with vs. <hi>If any man loue me, he will keepe my word, and my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will loue him, and wee will come vnto him, and dwell with him.</hi> They are the words of our Sauiour; Let vs therefore doe what he requires, and he wil aſſuredly performe what he promiſes. Let vs loue him, ſerue him, and keep his commandements cheerefully, and conſtantly, then will hee conſtantly take vp his habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation with vs in this life, and wee
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:177921:46"/>ſhall eternally poſſeſſe thoſe euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting habitations with him in the life to come. And ſo I come to <hi>Peters</hi> checke, <hi>Quid ad te? What is that to thee?</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="part">
                           <head>What is that to thee?</head>
                           <p n="4">4. ANd yet, to ſpeake ingenuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I come not very willingly to it. I vtterly diſlike that prying and cenſorious humour of them, who take delight to ſpie out <hi>the leaſt mote in the eye of others,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Math. 7.3.</note> and care not what aſperſions they caſt vpon them. Such are the brood of <hi>Cham.</hi> I had rather with <hi>Sem</hi> and <hi>Iapheth,</hi> couer the nakedneſſe of any ſeruant of God with the mantle of charity. Yet,
<note place="margin">Rom. 15.4.</note> foraſmuch as <hi>whatſoeuer was written afore time, was written for our learning;</hi> And the frailties of holy men are recorded in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<note place="margin">Chryſoſtom.</note> 
                              <hi>Vt caſus maiorum ſit tremor mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum,</hi> that the ſlips of men eminent
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:177921:46"/>in grace, may make vs, who are but vnderlings, to looke warily to our owne ſteps: It cannot be vnlawfull, or vnprofitable, to view them as Sea-markes, for our ſafer ſayling in the Ocean of this dangerous world.</p>
                           <p>And ſuch is this frailty of <hi>Peter,</hi> whom not onely diuers ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but many learned Papiſts alſo (whoſe vttermoſt indeauours haue not beene wanting to aduance the Romane See) haue thus cenſured. Onely Cardinall <hi>Tollet,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">In Locum.</note> of all that I remember, doth abſolutely denie, that <hi>Peters</hi> was a curious queſtion. To whom I may oppoſe two Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals, no leſſe learned, and as much deuoted to <hi>Peter</hi> &amp; the See of <hi>Rome</hi> as himſelfe, namely <hi>Caiet.</hi> &amp; <hi>Baron.</hi>
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Caietan. in Ioh.</hi> 21. <hi>Baron. Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>ad an.</hi> 34.</note> And <hi>Tollets</hi> reaſon is very weake to maintaine his paradox, <hi>Wee ſhould not eaſily belieue</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that Peter being lately and highly aduanced by Chriſt, ſhould ſo ſoone fall into curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity.</hi>
                              <pb n="84" facs="tcp:177921:47"/>To him S.
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Aug. de verb. dom. ſerm.</hi> 13.</note> 
                              <hi>Augustine</hi> ſhall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere for mee, vpon the like frailty of <hi>Peters, Petrus paulô ante beatus, postea Satanus, Peter,</hi> who a little before, for his worthy confeſſion, was called by our Sauiour bleſſed, was afterward for his inconſiderate diſſwaſion tearmed Satan. Yea ſaith S.
<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> 
                              <hi>Auſtin, In momento vno, infra pauca verba,</hi> almoſt in a moment, within a few words. And I thinke it ſafer that <hi>Peter</hi> bee cenſured for curioſity, then our Sauiour for an vniuſt checke;
<note place="margin">In hoc locum.</note> For, <hi>Chriſti reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio eſt cum obiurgatiuncula,</hi> Chriſts anſwere is with a checke, ſaith <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meron.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Indeed <hi>Bellarmine</hi> dares not take vpon him to iuſtifie, but doth one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly indeauour to qualifie this ſlippe of <hi>Peters,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Bellar. de Rom. Pontif.</hi> 1.28.</note> ſaying, <hi>Iſta ſi curioſitas di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenda, venia digniſsima eſt.</hi> If you call this curioſity, it is very pardona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, in regard of <hi>Peters</hi> loue to <hi>Iohn.</hi> To whom I doe willingly condiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend;
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:177921:47"/>yet this onely frees <hi>Peter,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">In part, not altogether.</note> 
                              <hi>a tanto,</hi> not <hi>à toto.</hi> Now, curioſitie <hi>in minutiſsimis,</hi> euen in the ſmalleſt matters is to be reſtrained, and auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, as S.
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Auguſt. confeſ.</hi> 10.35.</note> 
                              <hi>Augustine</hi> ſhewes in his Confeſſions. And ſo our Sauiours <hi>quid</hi> comes in here to checke <hi>Peters quid,</hi> like his <hi>ſi,</hi> to checke the mans <hi>ſi</hi> in the ninth of <hi>Marke, If thou canst doe any thing,</hi> ſaith the father of the poſſeſſed Childe;
<note place="margin">Mark 9.22.23</note> 
                              <hi>If thou canst be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue,</hi> ſaith Chriſt. For ſo, when <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> askes, <hi>Hic autem quid? What ſhall Iohn doe?</hi> Chriſt anſwers, <hi>Quid ad te? What is that to thee?</hi> And the Syriacke doubles the checke with an empheſis, <hi>Ad te, quid ad te? What is that to thee, to thee?</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>This curioſity, as it was the ſinne of our firſt Parents; ſo is deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to all their poſterity. Hence it is, that the boaſting Phariſee inſults ouer others ſo diſdainfully,
<note place="margin">Luke 18.11.</note> 
                              <hi>I am not as other men, extortioners, vniust, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterers, nor euen as this Publican.</hi>
                              <pb n="86" facs="tcp:177921:48"/>But, <hi>Quid ad illum? What hath hee to doe with that?</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Rom. 14.4.</note> 
                              <hi>Who art thou that iudgest another mans ſeruant?</hi> Hence it is that there are ſo many refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers of our Church, <hi>Etiam opifices quorum res fideſq<expan>
                                    <am>
                                       <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                    </am>
                                    <ex>que</ex>
                                 </expan> in manibus ſitae ſunt,</hi> Euen meere Handicrafts men, whoſe credit,
<note place="margin">Saluſt. de bello Iugurth.</note> wealth (and wit) lyes in their hands (as <hi>Salust</hi> ſpeakes of the Roman factious Plebeians) are very buſie this way. They thinke they ſee the Arke ſhake; and with <hi>Vzza,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">2 Sam. 6.6.</note> they will take vpon them to ſtay it: but <hi>quid ad eos,</hi> (if it were ſo) what haue they to doe with that? <hi>Who required this at their hands?</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Eſa. 1.12.</note> Yea, from this corrupt humour it comes, that there is ſcarce ſo meane a Mechanicke, or ſilly ruſticke, but is ready to cenſure the Church, the King, the State; but <hi>Quid ad eos?</hi> What haue they to do with matters and myſteries of State? <hi>Ne ſutor vltra crepidam,</hi> it becomes them well to keepe themſelues within
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:177921:48"/>their own <hi>lasts and lists;</hi> according to the Apoſtles aduiſe,
<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 4.11.</note> 
                              <hi>Let vs ſtudie to be quiet, &amp; to meddle with our own buſineſſe.</hi> It may be obiected that S. <hi>Paul</hi> exhorts vs to <hi>conſider other mens buſineſſe.</hi> And it is true;
<note place="margin">Phil. 2.4.</note> But there is <hi>ſollicitudo charitatis, &amp; curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſitatis,</hi> A care and conſideration of charitie, and the like of curioſitie; The one is to counſell, comfort, and relieue; the other onely to pry, to know, to cenſure. The one hath the warrant of a calling, the other ariſes forth of a pragmaticall diſpoſition, and is the trade of buſibodies: that the Apoſtle commends; this he condemnes.</p>
                           <p>But it is no meruaile that curioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is buſie with mens affaires, when it feares not to intrude it ſelfe into Gods ſecrets. One is buſily ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, when the day of Iudgement ſhall be? another queſtions why the world was made no ſooner? another what God did before he
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:177921:49"/>made the world?
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Aug. confeſſ. lib.</hi> 11. <hi>cap.</hi> 12.</note> 
                              <hi>To whom</hi> (as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith) <hi>it might well be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, Alta ſcrutantibus gehennam parauit,</hi> He was making hell for ſuch curious inquiſitors.</p>
                           <p>Whereſoeuer our Sauiour meets with this vice, it neuer goes without a checke. When the Diſciples de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of him,
<note place="margin">Act. 1.6, 7.</note> 
                              <hi>Lord wilt thou at this time restore the Kingdome to Iſrael?</hi> He tooke them vp thus, <hi>It is not for you to know the times or the ſeaſons, which the Father hath put in his owne power.</hi> Yea when his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaid to him at the marriage in <hi>Cana</hi> in <hi>Galile,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Ioh. 2.3, 4.</note> 
                              <hi>They haue no wine;</hi> He anſwered her, <hi>Woman what haue I to doe with thee? mine houre is not yet come. Neque Ambroſius veritus est dicere, Chriſtem arguiſſe matrem,</hi> And S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> was not afraid to ſay that Chriſt reproued his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſaith <hi>Ianſenius.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>When a buſie fellow was verie inquiſitiue concerning the gods,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:177921:49"/>
                              <hi>Euctid</hi> anſwered him well, <hi>Caeter a neſcio, illud ſcio quod odere curioſes,</hi> Other things I know not, but well I know that they hate curious que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioniſtes.</p>
                           <p>And indeed curioſitie doth iuſtly deſerue a checke. It is both odious and dangerous. <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">Prou. 25.1.</note> 
                              <hi>It is the Glorie of God to conceale a ſecret.</hi> And is it not then inglorious to him when men ſhall buſily and curioſly pry into that which he hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed?
<note place="margin">Rom. 11.34.</note> 
                              <hi>Who hath knowne the minde of the Lord? or who hath beene his councellor?</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle. Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie are we if we may be of his Court, though we be none of his Councell.
<note place="margin">Gen. 3.5.</note> It was a iuſt puniſhment vpon our firſt Parents that they were infatuated, for deſiring to match God in knowledge. And it is verie iuſt that thoſe, who in ſacred things will ſore beyond their pitch, haue the eies of their vnderſtanding dazled, and when they thinke to be
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:177921:50"/>moſt wiſe, turne fooles, like them in the firſt to the <hi>Romans.</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Rom. 1.22.</note> The men of <hi>Bethſhemeſh</hi> ſmarted verie worthily for prying into the Arke.
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 6.19.</note> And <hi>Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pey</hi> for ruſhing into the <hi>Sanctum ſanctorum.</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Munſt. coſmog. deſcrip. Italiae.</note> And did not <hi>Pliny</hi> loſe his life by his curious ſearching af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Mount <hi>Veſevus? Gods iudgments</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid) are like a great deepe;</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Pſal. 36.6.</note> and who is able to diue into the bottome of them? Not the bleſſed Apoſtle,
<note place="margin">Rom. 11.33.</note> who rather adores, admires then ſeekes to comprehend them. <hi>O altitudo, O the deepeneſſe of the riches both of the wiſdome and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God! How vnſearchable are his iudgements, and his waies past finding out!</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>That is an euill and a vſuall fruit of curioſitie, which S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaks of, <hi>Curioſitas inuenit haereſim,</hi> Curioſitie hath beene the author of hereſie. And what elſe hath incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred the Church with <hi>Arminius</hi> quiddities, and <hi>Vorſlius</hi> horrible
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:177921:50"/>blaſphemies, but proud curioſitie? And what elſe hath caſe diuers (from their diſlike of our Church gouernment) into thoſe lamentable gulfes of Browniſme, Anabaptiſme, Arianiſme? Curioſitie can finde no center to reſt on, but leades men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to endleſſe labyrinthes. It is a drunken humour, and intoxicates exceedingly. Therefore the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle exhorts men <hi>to vnderstand ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to ſobrietie.</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Rom. 12.3.</note> How haue the Schoolemen, &amp; ſome others puſled themſelues about that queſtion, why Chriſt ſhould loue <hi>Iohn</hi> more then the other Diſciples? I am not ignorant that diuers probable rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons may be rendred. But it is, in my iudgement, a meere curious queſtion, and deſerues a <hi>quid ad te?</hi> For, ſhall the ſeruant call his maſter, or the ſubiect his ſoueraigne to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt? Muſt Chriſt giue a reaſon to ſilly ſinfull men of his affections and actions? This is <hi>temeraria ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,</hi>
                              <pb n="92" facs="tcp:177921:51"/>as S.
<note place="margin">Raſh and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptious knowledge. <hi>Aug. de verb. Apl. Ser.</hi> 20. Exod. 19.12.</note> 
                              <hi>Austine</hi> calls it. It ſhall be our wiſdome, that we be content to be ignorant, where the Scripture is ſilent. As the Lord ſet markes and bounds at Mount <hi>Sinai;</hi> ſo hath he for the ſearching of his ſacred and ſecret councels. That is a worthy queſtion of <hi>Lactantius,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Lact. inſtitut. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 9.</note> 
                              <hi>Quid ergo quaeris, quae nec ſcire potes, nec ſi ſcias beatior fias?</hi> Why ſhould a man hunt after the knowledge of thoſe things, which he cannot attaine to? and which being attained to, can make him neuer a whit better or more bleſſed? If a man were the acuteſt Logitian, the moſt elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Orator, the profoundeſt Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematician in the world. If he knew all the motions, conſtellations, and influences of the heauens; and were able with <hi>Solomon</hi> to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of Beaſts, and Birds, and Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getables, from the Cedar of Liba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non to the Hyſop on the wall: Yet if that <hi>vnum neceſſarium</hi> be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,
<note place="margin">Luk. 10.42.</note>
                              <pb n="93" facs="tcp:177921:51"/>he doth but <hi>ex arena funiculos nectere.</hi> All that knowledge is but,
<note place="margin">Knit cords of Sand. <hi>Iren. l.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 45.</note> meere vanitie and idle curioſitie. It is <hi>wholeſome doctrine</hi> that makes a Chriſtian batle in grace.
<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.10.</note> One dram of Diuine knowledge tending to ſaluation, is more worth then all the abſtruſe ſpeculations of the moſt curious Artiſtes in the world.</p>
                           <p>That is good counſell of the Son of <hi>Syrach, In ſuperuacaneis rebus &amp;c.</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 3.24.</note> Be not curious in ſuperfluous mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Chryſ. in Ioh. hom.</hi> 23.</note> And that of <hi>Chryſostomes</hi> bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; <hi>Traduce hanc curioſitatem ad cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram ſalutis tuae,</hi> Change this curioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie into a care of thy ſaluation. And what elſe did our Sauiour intend, when to one asking,
<note place="margin">Luk. 13.24.</note> 
                              <hi>Lord are there many that ſhall be ſaued?</hi> He anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>Striue to enter in at the ſtrait gate.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, <hi>Quid ad te?</hi> What haſt thou to doe with the number of them that ſhall be ſaued? Rather conſider the difficultie, and know, it is thy dutie to vſe all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:177921:52"/>for the obtaining of eternall ſaluation. Therefore to conclude, if we will be inquiſitiue;
<note place="margin">Act. 9.6.</note> Let vs chang <hi>Peters quid</hi> into <hi>Paules quid, Act.</hi> 9. <hi>Domine quid me vis facere?</hi> Lord what wilt thou that I ſhall doe?
<note place="margin">Act. 16.30.</note> and into the Gaolers <hi>quid, Act.</hi> 16. <hi>Quid me oportet facere vt ſalvus fiam?</hi> Sirs what muſt I doe to be ſaued? and into <hi>Dauids quid,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Pſ. 116.12.</note> 
                              <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 116. <hi>Quid retribuam?</hi> What ſhall I render vnto the Lord for all his benefits towards me?
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.10.</note> Let vs <hi>Studie to make our electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſure,</hi> as S. <hi>Peter</hi> exhorts. Theſe indeede are worthy inquiſitions; this is a neceſſarie ſtudie; which, when all frothy curioſitie ſhall va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, will yeeld vs comfort in this life, and make vs eternally bleſſed in the life to come.</p>
                        </div>
                        <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                     </div>
                     <div type="sermon">
                        <pb n="95" facs="tcp:177921:52"/>
                        <head>THE SAFEST <hi>SERVICE.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <epigraph>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>IOHN. 21.22.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>Follow thou me.</p>
                           </q>
                        </epigraph>
                        <p>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OV haue heard that theſe words containe our Sauiours <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion,</hi> and his <hi>Iniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi> In the one he checkes <hi>Peter</hi> for his curioſitie. In the other he preſcribes him his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. In the Reprehenſion I noted the ſoueraigntie of Chriſts ſacred and ſecret will, concerning <hi>Iohn.</hi>
                           <pb n="96" facs="tcp:177921:53"/>Concerning which <hi>Peter</hi> being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſities heares from our Sauiour, that <hi>Quid ad te?</hi> What is that to thee? And now I come to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction, <hi>Follow thou me.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>It is a ſtrange ſpeech of <hi>Sanders</hi> in his ſixth Booke <hi>De Viſibili Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchia. In hoc toto ſermone Chriſtus nihil voluit aliis commune eum Petro eſſe.</hi> In all this ſpeech Chriſt would that no man ſhould haue any thing to doe but onely <hi>Peter.</hi> A moſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd and falſe poſition. For concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſome part of the ſpeech, Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                              <hi>De agone Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiana, cap.</hi> 30.</note> 
                           <hi>Cum ei dicitur om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus dicicur, Amas me? paſce oues incas.</hi> Where it is ſaid to <hi>Peter,</hi> Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt thou me? feed my Sheepe, it is ſaid to all Paſtors. And concerning the other,
<note place="margin">Euſeb. Emiſſ. Hom. de Iohan. Enangel.</note> 
                           <hi>Euſebius Emiſſenus</hi> ſaith in like tearmes, <hi>Quod Petro dicitur omnibus dicitur, Sequere me.</hi> That which is ſaid to <hi>Peter</hi> is ſaid to all, Follow me. Yea this is not ſpoken to the Diſciples onely, but to euerie
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:177921:53"/>particular Chriſtian.
<note place="margin">Simon de Caſſia</note> 
                           <hi>Quod Petro di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur ad ſequelam, omnibus dicitur ad regulam.</hi> It is a rule of direction to all men. As our Sauiour ſaid to the Diſciples of watching,
<note place="margin">Mark. 13.37.</note> 
                           <hi>What I ſay to you, I ſay to all men, watch:</hi> So may I ſay, What he ſaith to <hi>Peter,</hi> he ſaith to euerie man, <hi>Follow me.</hi> For euerie one hath giuen his name to Chriſt, and receiued the name of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an from Chriſt, becauſe he becomes his follower. Chriſt entertaines none into his ſeruice, but vpon that condition, <hi>If any man will come after me, let him denie himſelfe,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Luk. 9.23.</note> 
                           <hi>and take vp his croſſe, and follow me.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The ancient Fathers haue expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed this following of Chriſt in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers phraſes, by way of explication. <hi>Non paſſibus corporis, ſed cordis,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">And S. <hi>Bern. Non corpore ſed corde. S. Hier. in Mat.</hi> 20. <hi>Non pedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſed virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus. Aug. Hom.</hi> 23.</note> ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> This following is not corporall, but ſpirituall. We muſt follow Chriſt, not with the feet of the bodie, but with the affection of the heart. And Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> and
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:177921:54"/>
                           <hi>Gregorie</hi> likewiſe ſhew,
<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Greg in Euan. Hom.</hi> 19.</note> that this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of Chriſt is the imitating of him in holineſſe, and righteouſneſſe of life and conuerſation. Theſe are by <hi>Dauid</hi> called <hi>the pathes of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Pſ. 119.35.</note> 
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23.3. And <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. he deſires to tread them, ſaying, <hi>Make me to walke in thy commandements.</hi> The Seafaring man, that will be proſperous in his voyage, muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to himſelfe a ſafe hauen, a good way, and a skilfull Pilot. Behold here, Heauen is our Hauen, Chriſt Ieſus our Pilot, and for the way he hath giuen vs an exact Card. Yea he himſelfe is our <hi>Cynoſura,</hi> and our eye muſt be ſtill fixed vpon him,
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.2.</note> 
                           <hi>the Authour and finiſher of our Faith.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>It is true, <hi>We ſhould liue by rules, and not by examples.</hi> But this exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is beyond all rules.
<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Bern. in Cant. ſerm.</hi> 59.</note> 
                           <hi>Validior vox operis quàm oris,</hi> The voice of works is more forceable then the voice of words. Morall demonſtrations are more powerfull then all the Logical
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:177921:54"/>that can be deuiſed. The Phyſitian ſhall preuaile more with his Patient by taſting the medicine himſelfe, then by all the reaſons he can vſe. And behold Chriſt Ieſus is our gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Phyſition, and hath taken that courſe. He is our Captaine, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires no Souldier to ſet one foot further then himſelfe hath gone.</p>
                        <p>All other guides muſt be follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a <hi>Quatenus,</hi> as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Be you followers of me,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.1.</note> 
                           <hi>as I am of Christ.</hi> And reaſon. For albeit the bleſſed Apoſtles, as they were our Sauiours Secretaries, were priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged from error in matter of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; yet were they not from aber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of life and conuerſation. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> himſelfe did not <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>,
<note place="margin">Gal. 2.14.</note> 
                           <hi>He wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked not with a right foot.</hi> But this guide muſt be followed abſolutely in the pathes of his precepts and practiſe; as being an exact patterne of perfection.
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.16.</note> 
                           <hi>God manifested in the Fleſh, iustified in the Spirit, ſeene
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:177921:55"/>of Angels, preached of to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, beleeued on in the World, and receiued vp into Glorie.</hi> And he it is that ſaith, <hi>Follow thou me.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Theſe words I might diuide into three parts, according to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the words.</p>
                        <p>As firſt, an Action, <hi>Follow.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Second, the Agent, <hi>thou.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Third, the Obiect, <hi>me.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>But I intend for more plainneſſe to handle this Iniunction,
<note place="margin">Iointly rather then ſeuerally</note> 
                           <hi>coniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctim,</hi> rather then <hi>diuiſim;</hi> and in ſtead of thoſe three parts, to obſerue theſe three paſſages.</p>
                        <p n="1">1 The matters wherein we muſt follow Chriſt.</p>
                        <p n="2">2 The manner how wee muſt follow him.</p>
                        <p n="3">3 The motiues why we ſhould follow him.</p>
                        <p>Concerning the matters wherein wee muſt follow Chriſt; wee will conſider the ſame firſt <hi>Negatiuely,</hi> then <hi>Affirmatiuely.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <pb n="101" facs="tcp:177921:55"/>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Negatiuely,</hi> that we may ſee what pathes we are to auoyd in our fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of Chriſt.</p>
                        <p>And firſt, wee are not to follow him in his miraculous workes; they are no pathes for vs. And therefore where as our Sauiour ſaith, <hi>Mat. 11. Learne of mee,</hi> S. <hi>Augustine</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Aug. de bonis coniugal, c.</hi> 37.</note> what to doe? Not to create the world, to walke on the water, to raiſe the dead. Wee muſt follow him, <hi>Non in quantum filius Dei,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">
                              <hi>Aug. de ſanct. virgmit. ca.</hi> 27.</note> 
                           <hi>ſed in quantum ſilius hominis,</hi> Not as he was the ſonne of God, but as he was the ſonne of man, as the ſame Father ſaith. For in his miracles his diuine vertue did concurre with the huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.
<note place="margin">Mat. 14.19.</note> When he fed that multitude with fiue loaues and two fiſhes, the humanity did breake the bread, the diuinity did multiply it. When he raiſed <hi>Lazarus,</hi> the humanity ſaid,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 11.43.</note> 
                           <hi>Come forth,</hi> but the diuinity put life into him.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, As we muſt not attempt
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:177921:56"/>the following of Chriſt in his mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous workes: ſo muſt we not in his ſatisfactory, and meritorious. We may, we muſt follow him in thoſe, as occaſion ſhall be offered, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the matter, and the forme, but not in regard of the end. For alas, all other workes (be they actiue or paſſiue) come far too ſhort of merit and ſatisfaction. They muſt be of infinite value, that muſt merit and make ſatisfaction to the infinite Iuſtice of God; therefore we muſt leaue that alone to Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Eſ. 63.3.</note> who <hi>trod the wine preſſe alone.</hi>
                           <note place="margin">
                              <hi>Bernard. in Cant. ſer.</hi> 61.</note> And the beſt man liuing muſt ſay with S. <hi>Bernard, Meritum meum miſerationes domini,</hi> The Lords mercies are my merit.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, Wee are not bound to follow Chriſt in euerie circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall action of his, where we haue no precept. As for an inſtance, our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour did ordinarily ſit when he preached, as all the Euangeliſts doe ſhew. Yet is this no abſolute rule of
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:177921:56"/>direction to vs. He caſt himſelfe vpon his face in prayer, as we reade in the twentie ſixth of S. <hi>Mathew.</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Mat. 26.39.</note> We are not bound ſo to doe when we pray. And if he had ſit at the inſtitution of the Lords Supper, (which though many vrge, yet no man is able to proue to me) yet were we not bound therein to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate him without a precept.</p>
                        <p>Thus much for our direction ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiuely.</p>
                        <p>Now concerning the pathes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmatiuely.</p>
                        <p>Theſe I might diuide Scholaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally; But my deſire is to direct you the plaine way to Heauen, and ſo to commend vnto you ſome eſpeciall pathes wherein euerie faithfull Chriſtian muſt follow Chriſt, if euer he looke to come to Heauen after him.</p>
                        <p>The firſt and chiefeſt is the path of <hi>Pietie,</hi> which is <hi>Verus Deicultus,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Aug. epiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </note> The true worſhip of God, wherein
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:177921:57"/>our Sauiour walked abundantly. He preached in the day, and prayed in the night. He was zealous of Gods glorie,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 2.</note> 
                           <hi>euen to a conſumption,</hi> as it were; according to that in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of <hi>Iohn,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Iohn 2.17.</note> 
                           <hi>The zeale of thy Houſe hath eaten me vp.</hi> In ſo much that when hee ſaw God diſhonoured and his Houſe profaned, though hee were the meekeſt that euer liued, yet was hee moued with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, and whipt the buyers and ſellers out of dores. And ſo ſhould euerie good Chriſtian take it to heart, when hee ſees God diſhonoured.</p>
                        <p>Thus the Magiſtrate in ruling, the Miniſter in preaching, and euerie Chriſtian, in reuerend hearing of the Word, deuout calling vpon the Name of God, and religious recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the Sacrament, muſt indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour the aduancement of Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, &amp; ſo follow our bleſſed Sauiour in the pathes of Pietie.</p>
                        <pb n="105" facs="tcp:177921:57"/>
                        <p n="2">2. The ſecond path, wherein we muſt follow Chriſt, is the path of Chriſtian <hi>Loue and Charitie,</hi> and this we muſt haue both <hi>Actu &amp; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectu,</hi> in action and affection.
<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Bern. in Cant. Serm.</hi> 50.</note> If one giue a poore man good words,
<note place="margin">Iam. 2.16.</note> 
                           <hi>and giue him not thoſe things which are needfull to the body, what helpeth it?</hi> And <hi>if a man ſhould feed the poore,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.3.</note> 
                           <hi>and giue his body to be burned, and haue not loue, it profiteth nothing.</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Ephe. 5.1, 2.</note> 
                           <hi>Be you followers of God as deare children</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>and walke in loue as Chriſt hath loued vs, and giuen himſelfe for vs.</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Coloſſ. 3.14.</note> This loue is <hi>the bond of perfection, and the badge of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianitie.</hi> Yea that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 13.35.</note> 
                           <hi>as Christ hath loued vs,</hi> calles both for the manner and meaſure of our loue, both intenſiue and extenſiue: it muſt be intenſiue as our Sauiours was.
<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Charitatem exigit intenſam Chryſoſt. in</hi> 1. <hi>Cor. hom.</hi> 32. 1. Ioh. 3.16.</note> 
                           <hi>As hee ſo loued vs, that hee laide downe his life for vs; we ought alſo to lay down our liues for the brethren.</hi> 2. It muſt be extenſiue. As Chriſt
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:177921:58"/>loued vs euen when we were ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. So muſt we doe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept wee will be meere Phariſes. <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. Such was his loue and compaſsion to his enemies, that in the middeſt of all their rage and fury he prayed for them.
<note place="margin">Luke 23.34.</note> 
                           <hi>Father, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue them, for they know not what they doe.</hi> And the like he requires of vs, ſaying, <hi>Loue your enemies: bleſſe them that curſe you;</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Math. 5.44.</note> 
                           <hi>doe good to them that hate you, and pray for them that perſecute you; that you may be the children of your Father which is in heauen.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="3">3. The third eſpeciall path where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we muſt follow our Sauiour, is <hi>Humilitie.</hi> This is a leſſon which he commends vnto vs in eſpeciall man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, by his precept, and gratious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe annexed to it.
<note place="margin">Math. 11.29.</note> 
                           <hi>Learne of me that I am meeke &amp; lowly in heart, and you ſhall finde rest to your ſoules. Dux no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis fuit ad ſuperhiam,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">
                              <hi>Auguſt. hom.</hi> 12. <hi>ex</hi> 50.</note> The deuill (ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) was our ringlea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:177921:58"/>to pride, let vs follow Chriſt our guide to humilitie. And in this our Sauiour was an admirable pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne, as the Apoſtle ſhewes, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. For <hi>when he was equall to God,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Phil. 2.7.</note> 
                           <hi>he made himſelfe of no reputation,</hi> he did diſrobe himſelfe of his glory, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, euen emptied himſelfe as it were of his diuine dignitie, to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake a baſe and humble condition for our ſakes; and ſtooped downe from the throne of his Maieſtie, to raiſe vs vp who were fallen into the gulfe of miſery. This <hi>Humility</hi> is <hi>radix virtutum,</hi> euen the roote of all diuine vertues. For the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vallyes are fruitfull, when the higher mountaines are barreine.
<note place="margin">Iam. 4.6.</note> 
                           <hi>God reſisteth the proud and giueth grace to the humble.</hi> This vertue is not to be found in the gardens of Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, but to be learned in the ſchoole of our Sauiour. It is the foundation of our aduancement in heauen, and, the lower we lay this foundation,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:177921:59"/>the ſafer and ſtronger is our buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. S. <hi>Augustine</hi> compares heauen to a ſtately Palace with a lowe doore, a man muſt ſtoope that will goe into it. As it was with our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, ſo muſt it be with his ſeruants, there went an <hi>exinaniuit</hi> before an <hi>exaltauit,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Phil. 2.8, 9.</note> 
                           <hi>he humbled himſelfe, and God exalted him.</hi> For, ſo ſaith our Sauiour,
<note place="margin">Luke 18.14.</note> 
                           <hi>He that humbleth himſelfe ſhall be exalted.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="4">4. The fourth path wherein we muſt follow Chriſt is the path of <hi>Patience,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">
                              <hi>Lactant. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 23.</note> which is, <hi>Malorum aequani mitate perlatio,</hi> moderate &amp; patient bearing of iniuries and euils. And <hi>hereunto you are called,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.21.</note> 
                           <hi>ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle Peter. For Christ alſo ſuffered for vs, leauing vs an example that we ſhould walke in his ſteppes.</hi> Oh the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracefull ſcoffes and mockes that he was ſubiect to! the reprochfull taunts and reuilings that he indured! the extreame violence that he ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained, and all this with admirable
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:177921:59"/>and vnmooueable patience! When he came to a Citie of the Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanes that would not entertaine him, the Diſciples,
<note place="margin">Luke 9.55.</note> forth of their vehement indignation, would haue called for fire from heauen: but he rebuked them, ſaying, <hi>You know not of what ſpirit you are.</hi> In the middeſt of all iniuries and oppoſitions, ſuch was his meekeneſſe and patience, <hi>That he did not ſtriue,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Math. 12.19.</note> 
                           <hi>neither was his voice heard in the ſtreetes.</hi> When he was led as a ſheepe, not only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſhearer, but euen the ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer, he was dumbe, and opened not his mouth. And all this he,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 53.7.</note> who in his humane nature was nobly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended of the blood Royall, and in his diuine was and is <hi>God bleſſed for euer,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Rom. 9.5.</note> indured at the hands of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, baſe, and ſinfull wretches.</p>
                        <p n="5">5 The fift eſpeciall path where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we muſt follow Chriſt, is the path of <hi>Obedience.</hi>
                           <note place="margin">
                              <list>
                                 <item>In Affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</item>
                                 <item>In Action.</item>
                                 <item>In Paſſion.</item>
                              </list>
                           </note> In which as he walked, ſo muſt we <hi>affectiuè, actiuè,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:177921:60"/>paſsiuè,</hi> as the Schooleman ſpeakes. For the firſt, he applyed his will to his Fathers will, ſaying, <hi>Not as I will, but as thou wilt:</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Math. 26.39.</note> and ſo muſt we, that we may ſay with them, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.14. <hi>The will of the Lord be done.</hi> In his Actiue obedience likewiſe he was ready and reſolute; Yea profeſſed himſelfe to be in the number of thoſe,
<note place="margin">Heb. 10.7. <hi>Calv. in Loc.</hi>
                           </note> 
                           <hi>who are in the Lords Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of obedient ſeruants.</hi> And ſo as we pray, <hi>thy will be done,</hi> we muſt be willing to doe it. But in his Paſſiue obedience he was yet more admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
<note place="margin">Phil. 2.8.</note> when <hi>hee was obedient to the death, euen the death of the croſſe.</hi> And ſo muſt we endeauour to <hi>ſettle our hearts,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Iam. 5.8.</note>
                           <note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.17.</note> that, <hi>if it be the Lords will to call vs to the fiery triall,</hi> we may be able to ſay with that bleſſed A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>I am ready not only to bee bound,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Acts 21.13.</note> 
                           <hi>but alſo to dye for the name of the Lord Ieſus.</hi> Loe, theſe are ſome of thoſe eſpeciall pathes, wherein we muſt follow Chriſt, that by them
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:177921:60"/>we may be guided to the kingdome of heauen.</p>
                        <div type="part">
                           <p n="2">2. BVt <hi>forma dat eſſe.</hi> And the manner of our walking con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth much to the <hi>Bene eſſe</hi> of our following Chriſt.
<note place="margin">The well being.</note> For the beſt ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices we take in hand, or tender to God, if they want their due forme, can finde neither reſpect nor reward from his hands. Therefore we will conſider the manner how we muſt follow Chriſt, which is the ſecond maine point I propoſed. And in this there are foure eſpeciall circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances to be obſerued.</p>
                           <p>Firſt, Wee muſt ſee, that we fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Chriſt <hi>ſincerely.</hi> For ſinceritie is that which ſeaſons all our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and makes them acceptable to Almightie God. This the Lord required of <hi>Abraham</hi> in that mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall couenant, <hi>Geneſis</hi> 17.
<note place="margin">Gen. 17.1.</note> 
                              <hi>Walke before me, and be thou vpright.</hi> And concerning this <hi>Dauid</hi> gaue that
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:177921:61"/>charge to <hi>Salomon</hi> his ſonne,
<note place="margin">1. Chro. 28.9.</note> 
                              <hi>That he ſhould ſerue the Lord with an vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right heart.</hi> Our Sauiour manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted his hatred to Hypocriſie, by thoſe many <hi>woes</hi> thundred out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it,
<note place="margin">Math. 23.</note> and admoniſhed his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples to beware of that Phariſaicall leauen. And reaſon; for it eates out the ſweetnes of religion; and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly where religion begins in hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, it ends either in Atheiſme, or Apoſtaſie. This is the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of hypocrites,
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Boni videri vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunt ſed non eſſe, &amp;c. Bern. in Cant. Serm.</hi> 66. Prou. 21.1. Pſal. 51. Mich. 6.7. Prou. 23.26.</note> 
                              <hi>They would ſeeme to be good, but will not be ſo: they will be euill, but would not ſeeme ſo.</hi> But <hi>the Lord pondereth the Spirits,</hi> and <hi>loues truth in the inward parts.</hi> It is not the <hi>thouſands of rammes, nor ten thouſand riuers of oyle, that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards.</hi> It is the ſincere heart that he delights in. Ruſtie gold is better then the brighteſt braſſe; And ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie, though in weakeneſſe, is a thouſand times better then pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pous hypocriſie. Whatſoeuer poore
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:177921:61"/>ſeruices therfore we are able to ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to God, let them be done in ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie, &amp; ſinglenes of heart: that we may heare from our Sauiour that <hi>Euge ſerue bone,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Math. 25.23.</note> Wel done thou good ſeruant and faithfull, thou haſt bin faithfull in a little, I will make thee ruler ouer much. And ſet downe this for an axiom, <hi>An hypocrite is no fit follower for Chriſt.</hi> 2. We muſt follow Chriſt <hi>diligently &amp; reſolutely.</hi> As our Sauiour, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he went to Ieruſalem, where he was to be perſecuted, and put to death; the Euangeliſt ſaith, <hi>He ſetled himſelfe fully,</hi> or,
<note place="margin">
                                 <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                                    <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                                 </gap>. Luke 9.51.</note> as it is in the originall, <hi>He hardned his face to goe to Ieruſalem.</hi> And therefore the Scriptures yeeld ſuch phraſes, as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire this diligence &amp; reſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. We muſt <hi>aske, ſeeke, knock,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Math. 7.7.</note> that the doore of mercy may be opened to vs.
<note place="margin">
                                 <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                                    <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                                 </gap>.</note> We muſt <hi>ſtriue, like Champions, to enter in at the ſtraite gate.</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Luke 13.24.</note> Can a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter indure to ſee his ſeruant goe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zily about his buſineſſe? ſurely no;
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:177921:62"/>neither can the Lord. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is a curſe denounced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him that doth the <hi>worke of the Lord negligently.</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Ierem. 48.10.</note> He that loues a cheerefull giuer, loues a cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full follower.
<note place="margin">Neceſſitas ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet timorem libertas amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem. Aug.</note> Careleſſe following argues want of loue, and the Lord cares little for it. I know, beloued, it is with vs in our actions, as it is with the motion of a clocke which growes weake and flag by degrees; As <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> obſerues of <hi>Peter: Caepit ambulare longinquius,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Math. 4.20.</note> he that at firſt, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap> 
                              <hi>immediately followed Chriſt,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Math. 26.58.</note> began at laſt <hi>to follow him ſlowly.</hi> Theorefore when we finde the motion of our Chriſtian endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours to waxe weake, wee muſt winde vp the plummets by earneſt and feruent prayer, that ſo we may follow our Sauiour reſolutely and diligently.</p>
                           <p>Thirdly, We muſt follow Chriſt <hi>totally.</hi> We muſt not obſerue the commandements of the firſt table,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:177921:62"/>and neglect the ſecond; for that is plaine hypocriſie: nor obſerue the ſecond and neglect the firſt, for that is meere moralitie. We muſt not be like <hi>Herod,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Mark. 6.20.</note> who <hi>heard Iohn Baptiſt gladly, and did many things,</hi> but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued to keepe one eſpeciall ſinne,
<note place="margin">Iob 20.12.</note> like a ſweet morſel <hi>vnder his tongue.</hi> We muſt not be like the Iewes, who <hi>drew neere to the Lord with their lips,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Iſa. 29.13.</note> 
                              <hi>but their hearts were farre from him;</hi> but we muſt ſay with <hi>Dauid,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Pſal. 75.7.</note> 
                              <hi>O God my heart is prepared.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>We muſt not attribute our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion partly to the merits of Chriſt, and partly to the merits of men; but we muſt ſay with that bleſſed mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, <hi>Only Christ, only Chriſt.</hi> Wee muſt not halt betweene two religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<note place="margin">1. Reg. 18.21.</note> as the Iſraelites <hi>did betweene two opinions.</hi> The Lord, in the time of the Law could not abide any gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to bee made of linnen and woollen: And ſurely he cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide any linſie wolſie profeſſors of
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:177921:63"/>the Goſpel. He can be no good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant to Chriſt, that is a ſecret retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to Antichriſt. Chriſt is like the naturall mother of the childe,
<note place="margin">1. Reg. 3.26.</note> that would either haue all or none of it. Therefore when the yong man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired that he might goe and burie his father, our Sauiour anſwered, <hi>Let the dead bury the dead,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Math. 8.22.</note> 
                              <hi>follow thou me.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, If thou wilt be my follower, thou muſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally addict thy ſelfe to me. Now this is not <hi>invidentiae,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Bern. in Pſal.</hi> 91. <hi>Serm</hi> 8.</note> 
                              <hi>ſed prouiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae: Totum ſibi manere inbet, ne tibi pereat.</hi> Chriſt doth this forth of his ſingular prouidence: He would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue all to himſelfe, leſt all periſh and be loſt to thee, ſaith <hi>Bernard.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Fourthly, We muſt follow Chriſt <hi>Conſtantly.</hi> Religion is in Scripture compared to a walke, which tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches vs that we muſt not ſerue God by fits. We muſt imitate the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels on <hi>Iacobs</hi> ladder,
<note place="margin">Gen. 28.12.</note> that were ſtill going vp and downe. We muſt not
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:177921:63"/>follow Chriſt only when he is fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed with <hi>Hoſannaes,</hi> but euen when he is purſued with <hi>Crucifiges.</hi> This was the fault of the Galathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, that they <hi>began well,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Gal. 5.7.</note> yet <hi>did not perſeuere,</hi> but were like <hi>Ephraim,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Pſal. 78.9.</note> who <hi>turned backe in the day of bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell:</hi> And ſo are there many that haue good motions, good meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and purpoſes to follow Chriſt, but they ſuffer them to vaniſh, and, <hi>they ſtart aſide like deceitfull bowes.</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Pſal. 78.57.</note> It was to ſmall purpoſe that <hi>Lots</hi> wife departed out of Sodome, when for looking backe ſhe was <hi>turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a piller of ſalt.</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Gen. 19.26.</note> Nor as it much, that the Iſraelites went out of Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, when for their murmuring they periſhed in the wildernes. Our Sauiour ſuffered many afflictions in his paſſion,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 19.30. It is finiſhed.</note> but neuer reſted till there was a <hi>conſummatum eſt.</hi> And this was the praiſe and happineſſe of <hi>Caleb,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Numb. 14.24</note> that <hi>he followed the Lord conſtantly.</hi> His happineſſe I ſay, for
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:177921:64"/>
                              <hi>Sola perſeuerantia coronatur,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Bern. Serm.</hi> 1. <hi>in Paſcha.</hi>
                              </note> ſaith <hi>Bernard:</hi> Only perſeuerance gaines the crowne of glory. And ſo ſaith our Sauiour,
<note place="margin">Math. 10.22.</note> 
                              <hi>He that indures to the end ſhall bee ſaued.</hi> According to which method he made his prayer a little before his death; <hi>I haue glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified thee on earth,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Ioh. 17.4.</note> 
                              <hi>I haue finiſhed the worke thou gaueſt me to doe, and now O Father glorifie me.</hi> And the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Apoſtle after the ſame manner concludes very comfortably, <hi>I haue fought the good fight, I haue finiſhed my courſe,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.8.</note> 
                              <hi>I haue kept the Faith, henceforth there is laid vp for me a crowne of righteouſneſſe, which the Lord the righteous iudge ſhall giue me at that day.</hi> And ſo much briefely for the manner how we muſt fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Chriſt.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="part">
                           <p n="3">3. NOw to the motiues, which may induce vs thus to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Chriſt;
<note place="margin">1. From matter of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie.</note> which I may reduce to theſe three heads: the 1. <hi>ab aequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate,</hi>
                              <pb n="119" facs="tcp:177921:64"/>the 2. <hi>à periculo,</hi> the 3.
<note place="margin">
                                 <p n="2">2. From the danger of neglect.</p>
                                 <p n="3">3. From the benefits which accrew by following him.</p>
                              </note> 
                              <hi>à bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficio.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="1">1. And firſt the fauours and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies wee haue receiued from our bleſſed Sauiour, ſhould in equitie be vnto vs a ſtrong bond of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. <hi>In odore vnguentorum,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Cant. 1.2, 3.</note> In the odour of his ſweet oyntments wee ſhould runne after him. As blind <hi>Bartimeus,</hi> when he was reſtored to his ſight, <hi>followed him in the way:</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Marke 10.52.</note> ſo ſhould we in thoſe waies I haue mentioned. <hi>Eum ſequebantur,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Bernard in feſt. Dom. ſanct. Serm.</hi> 1.</note> 
                              <hi>quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſaluabat animas ſanabat corpora.</hi> Thoſe became Chriſts followers, whoſe bodies he healed, and whoſe ſoules he ſaued. And reaſon: For theſe are the <hi>cords of men,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Hoſ. 11.4.</note> 
                              <hi>and the bonds of loue</hi> that <hi>Hoſe</hi> ſpeakes of. And to this purpoſe it is, that <hi>Samuel</hi> exhorts the children of Iſrael <hi>to conſider the great things the Lord hath done for them.</hi> As,
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 12.24.</note> when <hi>Elias</hi> had caſt his mantle ouer <hi>Elizeus,</hi> he followed him: ſo ſhould we follow
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:177921:65"/>our bleſſed Sauiour, who hath couered our iniquiries with the mantle of his merits. Thus <hi>Marie Magdelen,</hi> hauing receiued by him the pardon of her ſinnes, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to her ſoule, followed him to his Croſſe, to his graue, and neuer left him till he left the world.</p>
                           <p n="2">2 The ſecond motiue is <hi>à periculo.</hi> For the neglect of this is full of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice and danger. The Lord threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened the Iſraelites,
<note place="margin">1. Reg. 9.6.</note> 
                              <hi>1. Reg. 9.6.</hi> That <hi>if they turned away from him, he would cast them out of that Land he had giuen them.</hi>
                              <note place="margin">As appeareth, <hi>Cap.</hi> 11.</note> The wofull accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment whereof, they found by experience. And no meruaile that ſuch a mans caſe is dangerous; for he is like the Souldier that flies from his Captaine into the Campe of the Enemie. He expoſeth himſelfe to a double miſerie. Firſt, he is in the hands of Satan, a deadly Enemie. And albeit he may for a time be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained kindly into his Campe,
<note place="margin">Iudg. 4.18.21</note> as
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:177921:65"/>
                              <hi>Siſera</hi> was into <hi>Iaels</hi> Tent; yet let him looke for a hammer &amp; a naile, which will faſten him to a wofull condition. Againe, as ſuch a reuol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Souldier by his flying looſeth the protection of his Captaine: So this poore Soule by his flinching, is depriued of that comfortable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, which he ſhould haue by Ieſus Chriſt; according to the words of <hi>Azariah,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">2 Chro. 15.2.</note> 
                              <hi>The Lord is with you whilest you are with him; but if you forſake him, he will forſake you.</hi> Yea he not onely looſeth that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable protection, but incurres alſo Chriſts heauie indignation. As it was with the Iſraelites when they reuolted; ſo will it be with him; <hi>Whither ſoeuer they went,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Iudg. 2.15.</note> 
                              <hi>the hand of the Lord was against them.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="3">3 The third motiue is <hi>à beneficio.</hi> From the benefit we ſhall receiue by following Chriſt in theſe pathes of holineſſe and righteouſneſſe.</p>
                           <p n="1">1 And firſt, theſe pathes are <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable.</hi>
                              <pb n="122" facs="tcp:177921:66"/>This <hi>Peter</hi> knew well. For when our Sauiour ſeeing many of his followers become flinchers, ſaid to the twelue Diſciples,
<note place="margin">Iohn 6.68.</note> 
                              <hi>Will you alſo goe away? Peter</hi> anſwered, <hi>Master, to whom ſhould we goe? Thou hast the words of eternall Life.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, God forbid we ſhould forſake thee: for then we may ſay, farewell to all our hope of eternall happines. Yea this following of Chriſt yeelds comfort both in health and ſicknes, in life and death.
<note place="margin">Iob 23.11.</note> Thus did <hi>Iob</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort himſelfe in the middeſt of all his afflictions; <hi>My foot hath followed his ſteps: his way haue I kept, and not declined.</hi>
                              <note place="margin">2 <hi>Reg.</hi> 20.3.</note> And ſo did <hi>Hezechiah</hi> on his ſicke bed: <hi>Remember I beſeech thee, O Lord, that I haue walked be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee in truth and with a perfect heart, &amp; haue done that which is good in thy ſight.</hi> Thus when all other comforts faile; <hi>Conſcientia bene actae vitae,</hi> This ſhall be the only comfort of euerie good Chriſtian, that hee
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:177921:66"/>hath beene a fathfull follower of Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
                           <p>Secondly, As theſe pathes are comfortable; ſo are they honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>De Aduent. Dom. ſerm.</hi> 6.</note> 
                              <hi>Non erit tibi indignum ſequi au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorem tuum,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi> yea, It ſhall be thy happineſſe to follow thy founder and Maker. If wee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme it our honour to be the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of mightie Princes, how much more to follow Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Reu. 19.16.</note> 
                              <hi>The King of Kings?</hi> If the Queene of Sheba pronounced them happie,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Reg.</hi> 10.8.</note> who attended vpon <hi>Solomon,</hi> a pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and a potent King; how much more are we bleſſed in waiting vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Chriſt Ieſus, who is <hi>Omnipotent,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Math. 28.18.</note> and <hi>In whom are hid all the treaſures of wiſedome and knowledge?</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Col. 2.3.</note>
                              <note place="margin">Eccl. 23.28.</note> 
                              <hi>It is great glorie</hi> (ſaith the Son of <hi>Syrach) to follow the Lord.</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Math. 11.30. <hi>Auguſt. de temp. ſer.</hi> 182.</note> Chriſt tels vs that his <hi>yoke is eaſie. Iugum eius merito est ſuaue, cui ſcruire eſt regnare,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Auſtin:</hi> His yoke is light and ſweet indeed, whom to ſerue is to raign as
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:177921:67"/>
                              <hi>Kings.</hi> And for our comfort and incouragement, in following of Chriſt, behold the Saints of God, who as <hi>a cloud of witneſſes</hi> are gon before vs.
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.</note> We haue their worthy examples for our direction: wee haue their prayers for our ſafe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoye: and their expectation for our happie arriuall.</p>
                           <p>Againe, theſe pathes are the pathes of <hi>ſafetie.</hi> A good way, and a good guid are great comforts to a traueller; and this is our comfort in following Chriſt:
<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.6.</note> For he himſelfe is our way and our guid. <hi>He is the way,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Iohn 8.12.</note> 
                              <hi>the truth, and the life. He is the light of the world; he that followeth him, ſhall not walke in darkeneſſe, but ſhall haue the light of life.</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Prou. 14.12.</note> 
                              <hi>There is a way</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon) that ſeemes good to a man in his owne eyes, but the iſſue thereof is death.</hi> But theſe pathes are <hi>the pathes of life.</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Prou. 12.28.</note> We ſay that hee which walkes in the kings high way walkes ſafely, for he is vnder the
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:177921:67"/>Kings protection. And ſuch is his caſe that followes Chriſt in theſe pathes of holineſſe and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; he is in the high way to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and hath a Diuine protection, as it is written in the <hi>91. Pſalme,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Pſ. 91.11.</note> 
                              <hi>He ſhall giue his Angels charge ouer thec, to keepe thee in all thy waies, that thou daſh not thy foot againſt a ſtone.</hi> It is verie obſerueable throughout the ſacred Story of the Euangeliſts,
<note place="margin">Marke 8.2. <hi>Et paſſim.</hi>
                              </note> that our Sauiour had a continuall care, that none, who followed him, ſhould want. Yea he, that at the time of his apprehenſion had not a word of defence for himſelfe, had a <hi>Sinite hos abire,</hi> for his Diſciples.
<note place="margin">Let theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part. Ioh. 18.8</note> And it was his great glorie, that hee could ſay,
<note place="margin">Iohn 17.12.</note> 
                              <hi>Thoſe that thou haſt giuen me, I haue kept, &amp; none of them is loſt but the child of perdition:</hi> And hee was that trecherous Souldier I ſpake of.</p>
                           <p n="4">4 Laſtly, as theſe pathes are the pathes of ſafetie, ſo are they the
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:177921:68"/>pathes of <hi>felicitie.</hi> The Lord takes it verie kindly at the hands of the Iſraelites, as wee ſee in the ſecond of <hi>Ieremie;</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Ier. 2.2.</note> 
                              <hi>I remember the kindneſſe of thy youth and the loue of thy mariage, when thou wenteſt after me in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe.</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Bernard.</note> 
                              <hi>Eius reminiſci eſt remune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rari,</hi> His kind remembrance imports a recompence, ſaith <hi>Bernard.</hi> And no maruaile: for Maſters, that are of a noble and generous diſpoſition, will not ſuffer their ſeruants to be vnrewarded; much leſſe will Chriſt Ieſus. The Lord ſaid of <hi>Caleb,</hi> that to him he would giue the Land of Canaan,
<note place="margin">Deut. 1.36.</note> becauſe <hi>he had conſtantly followed the Lord.</hi> And ſo ſhall thoſe, who are conſtant followers of Chriſt, poſſeſſe the celeſtial Canaan, the Kingdome of Heauen.</p>
                           <p>As <hi>Henoch walked with God,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Heb. 11.5.</note> 
                              <hi>and was tranſlated, that he ſhould not ſee death:</hi> So thoſe that walke with Chriſt in theſe holy pathes, ſhall be partakers of eternall life; according
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:177921:68"/>to that in the twelfth of <hi>Iohn,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Ioh. 12.26.</note> 
                              <hi>If any man ſerue me, let him follow me; for where I am, there ſhall alſo my ſeruant be.</hi> As he that followes ſome great Riuer, ſhall by it be guided to the Sea: So thoſe that follow Chriſt, ſhall by him be conducted to the Ocean of eternall felicitie. And ſo our Sauiour told his Diſciples, and that with an aſſeueration for ratifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; <hi>Verely I ſay vnto you,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Mat. 19.28.</note> 
                              <hi>that when the Son of Man ſhall ſit in the Throne of his Maieſtie, you that haue followed me in the regeneration, ſhall ſit alſo vpon Thrones, and iudge the twelue Tribes of Iſrael.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="part">
                           <head>Application.</head>
                           <p>THus haue you heard the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, the manner, &amp; the motiues for our following of Chriſt. Now it remaines, that I conclude all with ſome words of <hi>application,</hi> and ſo finiſh my ſpeech. S. <hi>Auguſtines</hi>
                              <pb n="128" facs="tcp:177921:69"/>diſcourſe, in his ſeuenth Sermon, <hi>De Verbis Domini,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Ordine ali quantulum mutato.</note> ſhall be my ground. There were (ſaith Saint <hi>Augustine</hi>) three men of ſeuerall diſpoſitions and inclinations that came to Chriſt with whom he dealt accordingly.</p>
                           <p n="1">
                              <hi>1 Vnus differebat, &amp; culpatus eſt.</hi> One deferred to follow him, and he was blamed. So are there many that deferre and neglect this follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt. Some intend to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come his followers, but they put it off till ſickneſſe, or old age ſeaze vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them; till Sinne and Satan hath caſſiered them; and they are able to do Chriſt little ſeruice. Some there are who doe totally neglect this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of Chriſt. They are enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by the Fleſh, the World, and the Deuill; yea any thing but Chriſt: though the waies wherein they walke yeeld nothing but vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and miſerie. Thus the young man in the <hi>Prouerbes</hi> followes the ſtrange woman,
<note place="margin">Prou. 7.22.</note> 
                              <hi>like a foole to the
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:177921:69"/>ſtockes, and an oxe to the ſlaughter, till a dart ſtrike through his Liuer.</hi> Thus <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> imbracing the world,
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.10.</note> forſooke the Apoſtles. Thus riches caried away the man that ran to Chriſt.
<note place="margin">Marke 10.22.</note> For when he had giuen him histaske, he became a flincher, &amp; <hi>went away ſorrowfull.</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Caroclamat ego inficiam. Diabolus cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat, ego deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piam. mundus clamat, ego de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiam. Ego reficiam.</note> But what can theſe Maſters promiſe to their followers? Only that which S. <hi>Bernard</hi> mentions, <hi>The world, it cries, I will faile thee; the Deuill, he cries, I will deceiue thee, the Fleſh, it cries, I will infect thee. But come to me,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>and I will refreſh thee.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Satan is a maſter like <hi>Pharaoh;</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Exod. 5.14.</note> who ſet the Iſraelites all day on worke, and ſcourged them at night. For ſo doth the Deuill employ his Vaſſals, in the workes of iniquity in the time of their life, but at the day of their death, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them with the ſcourges of a troubled Conſcience, &amp; at the day of Iudgement, with helliſh torments. To Witches, and ſuch other wretches he promiſeth faire, but the end is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:177921:70"/>a ſhamefull death to their bodies, &amp; eternal condemnation to their Soules. The world is a maſter like <hi>Laban,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Gen. 31.41.</note> that <hi>changed Iacobs wages ten times, and would haue ſent him away emptie.</hi> Who would ſerue that maſter, which will keepe him hard in toyling, and in the end ſtrip him out of all he hath, and turne him away naked? Behold, the world is ſuch a maſter;
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.7.</note> for <hi>as wee brought nothing into the world: ſo it is certaine that we can carie out nothing. Naked came wee out of our mothers wombes,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Iob 1.21.</note> 
                              <hi>and naked must we returne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</hi>
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Saladine</hi> at his funerall had one going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his corps who carrying his ſhart vpon a launce, cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Saladine</hi> that Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of <hi>Aſia,</hi> caries nothing with him but this. <hi>Plat. in vit. Clem</hi> 3. Ier. 2.13.</note> The greateſt Monarches (as that great <hi>Saladine</hi> did well conſider) haue only a winding ſheet; or peraduenture ſome Monument, a meere monument of the worlds vanitie, &amp; mans morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie. I may truly ſay therefore, that thoſe who leaue Chriſt Ieſus to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the world, the Fleſh, or the Deuil, commit thoſe two euils that <hi>Ieremie</hi> mentions, <hi>They leaue the Fountaine of liuing waters, to dig to themſelues bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:177921:70"/>Cisternes that can hold no water.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="2">
                              <hi>2 Alius ſe obtulit &amp; reprobatus est.</hi> Another offered to follow Chriſt, and he was reiected. And indeed ſuch bad followers our Sauiour hath many: Some <hi>reſpectu formae,</hi> ſome <hi>reſpectu fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis:</hi> Some in reſpect of the forme, ſome of the ends. As it was in the daies of his infirmitie, ſo is it now in the daies of his maieſtie. Some fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed him for by-reſpects, ſome for bad reſpects. Some followed him to entangle him, as the Herodians.
<note place="margin">Mat. 22.16.</note> Some to betray him, as <hi>Iudas.</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Mat. 26.15.</note> Some only to gaine by him, as thoſe that followed him for the loaues &amp; the fiſhes.
<note place="margin">Iohn 6.26.</note> Chriſt hath ſome followers that are like Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mets, they are not fixed by a liuely Faith in Chriſt the Sphere of holines, but are caried about with an vncertain motion, according to ſome ſtar which rules them, &amp; they vaniſh accordingly.</p>
                           <p>Againe, ſome there are which faile in the manner of their following. As S. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpeakes of praying, ſo may
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:177921:71"/>I ſay of their following.
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Bern. de quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drageſ. Ser.</hi> 4.</note> Some follow Chriſt <hi>timidè,</hi> ſome <hi>tepidè,</hi> ſome <hi>teme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rariè.</hi> 1. Some follow him <hi>timidè,</hi> fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully. As <hi>Peter</hi> did when he was led to <hi>Annas</hi> &amp; <hi>Caiphas.</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Iohn 3.2.</note> As <hi>Nicodemus, that came to him by night.</hi> He durſt not be ſeene to be a follower of Chriſt. And thoſe rulers in the 12 of S. <hi>Iohn, which beleeued in him,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Iohn 12.42.</note> 
                              <hi>but were afraid to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe him.</hi> Thus euerie little rub turnes them aſide, whileſt they ſay. <hi>A Lyon is in the way:</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Prou 26.13.</note> 
                              <hi>A Lyon is in the ſtreetes.</hi> Theſe are like thoſe Iſraelites, who li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked well of the Land of Canaan,
<note place="margin">Numb. 13.33</note> but were afraid of the Anakims. It was a iuſt reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pence that they neuer entred into it.
<note place="margin">Reu. 3.</note> 2. Some follow Chriſt <hi>tepidè,</hi> coldly, like the Church of Laodicea. Theſe are like <hi>Solomons</hi> ſluggard,
<note place="margin">Prou 13.</note> 
                              <hi>Vult &amp; non vult piger.</hi> He could be content to follow Chriſt, but he cannot abide to take too much paines. Theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Chriſt ſo, as that they were as good to ſtay behind: he had rather haue their roome then their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany.
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:177921:71"/>He that wil be a welcome follower of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Acts 11.23.</note> muſt (as <hi>Barnabas</hi> exhorted) <hi>with full purpoſe of heart cleaue vnto the Lord.</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Cant. 1.3.</note> He muſt ſay with the Spouſe in the Canticles, <hi>Draw me, we will run after thee.</hi> And be reſolute with <hi>Ioſhua;</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Ioſh. 24.15.</note> 
                              <hi>Chuſe you this day whom you will ſerue; but I and mine houſe will ſerue the Lord.</hi> 3. Some follow Chriſt <hi>temerariè,</hi> raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Some march furiouſly with <hi>Iehu,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>An. dom.</hi> 1535 <hi>Sleidon. Com. lib.</hi> 10.</note> As the Anabaptiſts did in horrible vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rores &amp; combuſtions in Germany. The Papiſts, who in Q. <hi>Maries</hi> daies brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed out nothing but fire, &amp; fagots. In Q. <hi>Elizabeths,</hi> Piſtols, &amp; poiſons. And in the raign of our gracious ſoueraign, fire and gunpowder. Some inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratly betake themſelues to be Chriſts followers, but like fooliſh builders,
<note place="margin">Luke 14.28.</note> not counting what it may coſt them, they ſit downe with diſgrace; &amp; when the parching ſun of perſecution, or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction comes vpon them,
<note place="margin">Mat. 13.6.</note> like the <hi>ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ground, they wither away.</hi> Some a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine are ſo raſh, that they do <hi>Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:177921:72"/>Christum,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Aug. in Pſ.</hi> 62.</note> as S. <hi>Aug.</hi> ſaith, <hi>Whereas they ſhould follow Chriſt, they goe before him.</hi> Such as follow their own inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, rather then diuine direction: Such as haue zeale without diſcretion and iudgement: that thruſt their ſic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles into other mens harueſts, and run beyond the bounds of their calling: as many priuate men, who are very for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward about the reformation of the Church, yea, before themſelues be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed. Thoſe that would be wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to Chriſt, muſt follow him boldly, yet without preſumption; zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly, yet without contention; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creetly, without precipitation.</p>
                           <p>Thirdly ſaith S. <hi>Austin, Alius non au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debat, et excitatus est,</hi> One dared not to follow Chriſt, &amp; he was incouraged. I doubt not but it fares with many as it did with that man.
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Confeſſionum Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8.</note> S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> confeſſeth that he himſelfe was much perplexed when he was entring into religion. He thought thus with himſelfe; what ſhal become of me, when I become a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:177921:72"/>of the Goſpel? I ſhall loſe all my delights &amp; pleaſures; &amp; what comfort then ſhall I haue of my life? But it pleaſed God that theſe miſtes did va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh; and he found more true comfort to his ſoule, after he became a conſtant follower of Chriſt, then euer he did before. Inſomuch that he could ſay forth of experience,
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Aug. in Pſ.</hi> 117.</note> 
                              <hi>Dulcioros ſunt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrymae orantium, quàm gaudia thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trorum,</hi> Euen the teares of a Chriſtian ſhed in the middeſt of his prayers, are ſweeter then the ioyes and delights of the theaters. Beloued,
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Bonum Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num habemus. Amb.</hi> mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by <hi>Poſs. in vita Auguſt.</hi>
                              </note> why ſhould any one be diſcouraged to become a fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lower of Chriſt? nay, why ſhould not euerie one be incouraged? ſeeing he is ſuch <hi>a good master</hi> as will not faile to reward his ſeruants aboundantly.
<note place="margin">Reu. 22.12.</note> 
                              <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>I come ſhortly: and my reward is with me to giue euerie man according to his workes.</hi> If you remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber &amp; conſider the motiues, you need no further incouragement. The paths wherein you are to walke, are <hi>comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table,</hi>
                              <pb facs="tcp:177921:73"/>
                              <pb facs="tcp:177921:73" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                              <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                                 <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <pb n="120" facs="tcp:177921:74"/>
                              <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                                 <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <pb n="121" facs="tcp:177921:74"/>
                              <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                                 <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <pb n="122" facs="tcp:177921:75"/>
                              <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                                 <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <pb n="123" facs="tcp:177921:75"/>
                              <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                                 <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <pb n="124" facs="tcp:177921:76"/>
                              <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                                 <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <pb n="125" facs="tcp:177921:76"/>
                              <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                                 <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <pb n="126" facs="tcp:177921:77"/>
                              <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                                 <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <pb n="127" facs="tcp:177921:77"/>
                              <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                                 <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <pb n="128" facs="tcp:177921:78"/>
                              <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                                 <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <pb n="129" facs="tcp:177921:78"/>
                              <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                                 <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <pb n="130" facs="tcp:177921:79"/>
                              <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                                 <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <pb n="131" facs="tcp:177921:79"/>
                              <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                                 <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <pb n="132" facs="tcp:177921:80"/>
                              <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                                 <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <pb n="133" facs="tcp:177921:80"/>
                              <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                                 <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <pb n="134" facs="tcp:177921:81"/>
                              <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                                 <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <pb n="135" facs="tcp:177921:81"/>
                              <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                                 <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <pb n="136" facs="tcp:177921:82"/>and <hi>honorable;</hi> they are <hi>the pathes of ſafetie,</hi> &amp; <hi>eternall felicitie:</hi> feare not, neglect not therfore to follow Chriſt, though it be through fire and water. Your iourney may peraduenture coſt you ſome paines, cares, &amp; teares: yea <hi>fightings without,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">2 Cor. 7.5.</note> 
                              <hi>&amp; terrors within;</hi> but the end ſhal be ioyful &amp; comfortable. Heauen ſhall be your habitation; for Chriſt is gone before to prepare pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces there for his followers: and there you ſhall enioy his bleſſed preſence, &amp; bee partakers of ſuch ioyes, as neither eie hath ſeen, nor eare hath heard, nor can enter into the heart of man.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>The Lord, for his mercies ſake, giue vs grace to be faithful and constant follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of our Sauiour Christ in the waies of holineſſe and righteouſneſſe; that by the merits of his death and paſſion, we may be partakers of eternall bliſſe and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. To whom with the Father, and the holy Ghost, all honor, &amp; glorie, maiestie, and dominion be rendred, and aſcribed, world without end. Amen.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                        <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                        <pb facs="tcp:177921:82"/>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </text>
            </group>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
